2. Day 0 evening: Meditation Instructions

This is our first meditation instructions that we will be giving you this evening. We’ve mentioned that our meditation technique is known as satipatthana bhavana. Satipatthana is made up of two words: sati and patthana. We’re going to have to say much about this word and these practices called sati over the coming days. Its regular translation is mindfulness but we use the word awareness as well interchangeably. Mindfulness and awareness. Its meaning is attentiveness directed to the present moment. When we’re mindful, we are directing our attention to whatever is occurring in the present moment. So we’re directing our attention to the present. We are activating present moment awareness. We are switching it on, we are turning on our mindfulness. Patthana can have two meanings. It means either establishing or arousing. In its passive sense, it means establishing our awareness in the present moment or directing our attention in the present moment on to something, on to a foundation. There are four foundations that we will be talking about. Physical sensations, feelings, emotional states and thoughts – the four foundations on which mindfulness can be directed. Patthana can also have an active meaning. It means arousing. Arousing awareness in the present moment, arousing our attention in the present moment. So satipatthana, that is what our meditation practice is called.

We will be observing and activating our awareness in the present 16 moment on the very fast flowing range of objects. We will be starting with the physical sensations in the body, because they’re a little bit slower, a little bit grosser and easier to see. We will be transitioning in our meditation practice so that we can watch feeling, pleasant and unpleasant and emotional states and our thought patterns as well. Bhavana means mind development, mind cultivation or mind training.

So establishing mindfulness in the present moment on one of the four foundations of mindfulness – that’s what we are doing here this week. And your ability to establish your awareness in the present moment on whatever object is arising will lead you to see that object as it really is. We see things as they really are. And this is what is meant by clear seeing or Vipassana. Vi-passana. Pass means to see. Ana means it is a noun. Vi is an intensifying prefix. We are seeing things really clearly. We are seeing things so well, that the mind disengages, stops identifying with it, stops taking it as me, being for me or happening to me or as mine or as being I and let’s it go. We have clearly seen that object.

So satipatthana is the cause, Vipassana is the result. We establish our awareness in the present moment on one of the four foundations of mindfulness and that allows Vipassana to occur, clear seeing to occur.

And what is it that we’re having insight into? We’re observing not only the contents of our mind, but we’re observing the structure of our mind. We are seeing that all objects arise and pass away, but in particular all objects also have certain particular characteristics. They’re all impermanent, they’re all relatively unsatisfactory, in relation to the unconditioned element and they’re all non-self. They don’t belong to anybody. It’s all impersonal. It’s an impersonal flow that is going on.

When we see the structure of our experience in this way, it allows us to let go of things. The sense of self is let go surely and gradually. Thoughts of me, mine and I become less and eventually this leads to the complete cessation of being. The complete cessation of suffering. And that’s an experience the Buddha called nirvana – that cessation of dukkha.

Tonight, so that we can begin our practice, we have divided our instructions into three parts.

First of all we will be having a look at the practice of virtue, because 17 it’s one of the major conditions that we need to put in place. We will be having a look at our sitting meditation and also our walking meditation. These instructions are for the formal sitting and walking periods. The practice of virtue is all day everyday whilst we’re on the retreat. So be continuous in your mindfulness and practice throughout the day in order for Vipassana knowledge to unfold. As I said this afternoon, these Vipassana insights that arise from satipatthana meditation are conditioned. Conditioned by satipatthana. Conditioned by your ability to maintain your awareness in the present moment, to maintain your awareness internally, and your ability to continuously do this over and over again over a period of time. When these conditions are in place, the results start to flow naturally. As I said, there is nothing you can do to stop them from unfolding naturally in the mind.

2.1. Sila

The practice of sila or virtue begins with abstaining from unwholesome verbal and physical actions. The most gross of our three intentional doorways we have through body, speech and mind and our virtue practice will be to moderate our verbal actions and our physical actions. Purification of virtue is said by the Buddha to be the base upon which all other meditative practices are based. So if you are sincere in your effort and you wish to have the experience of insight, it is well recommended to you to maintain virtue. Tonight I’m not going to give you a sermon on morality but since the success of your meditation practice is conditioned by the practice of virtue, it’s worth taking note of these things. Of the noble eightfold path, the third, fourth and fifth factors are all concerned with virtue. So three out of eight factors of the noble eightfold path are to do with sila or morality.

The first one is called samma vaca, meaning right speech. Basically we are abstaining or stopping four types of unwholesome speech occurring. Of course in the retreat you’re all in silence. So this one is pretty much covered. For the sake of completeness we avoid telling lies to others. We avoid hard, rude speech to others. We avoid back stabbing others, that means talking about somebody to someone else in the hope that your opinion of that person will be conveyed to another person. The fourth one is gossiping.

The fourth factor of the noble eight fold path, samma kammanta means 18 right action. We abstain from three types of particular actions. We don’t kill anything, we don’t steal anything or take something which has not been given to us and we abstain from sexual misconduct. Sexual misconduct means relations with people that are inappropriate for us to have sexual relations with, whether they are people who are minors, or younger or children, whether they are people who are already in a relationship. Or even the kind of activity like raping somebody. This is all sexual misconduct. Adultery where taking someone’s husband or wife and having sexual relations with them. This is something that is very harmful for the other partner unless they have of course some agreement between themselves.

The fifth factor is samma ajiva or right livelihood. It means earning a living without harming anybody else. Having a right livelihood, having a livelihood which is beneficial for other beings. Specifically we avoid trading in things like guns or poisons or drugs or intoxicants. We try to make sure we don’t sell flesh from animals. We don’t make it to our business to be killing beings or taking unfairly the resources from other beings using them for ourselves or profiting by them for ourselves.

So we are practicing right speech, right action and right livelihood whilst we’re on the retreat here. This is a very firm base on which we can practice our meditation.

Whilst we’re on the retreat here, we will be following what is known as the eight precepts. In the morning we will chant the eight precepts. Basically they are no killing, no stealing, no lying, abstaining from sexual intercourse, abstaining from drugs and alcohol and abstaining from high and luxurious seats and beddings, abstaining from eating in the afternoon and not using any jewelry or flowers or trying to look fancy in any way, not listening to music or watching any shows.

An additional rule is not to speak with contempt about somebody who has already attained the noble eight fold path, somebody who has already become enlightened. You should be careful about this. This can disturb your meditation practice, maybe not in the beginning but later on, if ever you have said something detrimental or something negative about somebody who has become enlightened. You should make an apology – just in your own mind and then forgive yourself for making that mistake. That can clear certain 19 blockages away.

2.2. Sitting meditation

How do we do the sitting meditation? First of all we’re going to start to have a look at the position. When we’re sitting in meditation we need to try to be as comfortable as possible. We want to be comfortable for at least 45 minutes. That can be quite difficult in the beginning stages. When you’ve sat for a full session, you feel very much invigorated. You feel like you’ve been successful and you will find that you can sit for 45 minutes again and again and again once you have broken through that limit.

What I’m going to show you now is a few of the sitting postures. The most simple of them is just the cross legged position. It’s called sukhasana. Happy posture if you like. The problem with this posture is that all your weight will be distributed on to very small areas around your ankles and on to the sit bones. So after a while it becomes quite painful.

The second posture that we use as well is called the quarter lotus. That’s done by putting your foot up on the calf of the other leg. Normally, we put the left leg under the right leg. But other traditions have other styles. If your legs are not properly stretched, you will find some tension points underneath because there’s not a great deal of flatness.

Then we have what is know as the half lotus. Half lotus is the posture I like to sit in personally. We take the sole of our foot and tuck it into our groin. Nice and close and then you put the sole of your foot on the inside of your thigh. Your leg is kind of turned over a little bit that your anklebone is not even touching the floor. It’s kind of tucked under. All the weight is along this shinbone. So it’s a nice and continuous flat surface that doesn’t have any pressure points.

Another very comfortable posture is the posture that the Burmese monks and nuns like to take. It starts with the same thing, sole running on the inside of this thigh and then instead of putting it up on the thigh, leave it in front. That’s the most comfortable one. The most important thing is that you are flat and comfortable.

Those who want to get the little fancy can try to do the full lotus posture. Quite uncomfortable, quite painful for most people. You can get it 20 going for a few minutes and after that it starts to become uncomfortable. You can try to sit in the shallow water on the beach whilst you’re here on the island. Gravity in the water is a little bit different.

We mentioned this afternoon the numbness in the legs, which can quite often happen if we are leaning over our legs. So make sure that your back is up straight. If you start leaning forward, all the weight will go down on your legs and you start to get numb. If you find that you’re getting a little bit numb, you can try just to leaning back a little bit. For a minute or two you just lean back and take away the weight of your legs. We don’t want to be tense with our back. We are not trying to stretch the head and touch the roof, but we’re not leaning over either. You just want to be with a straight spine up in a row allowing the spine and skeleton to support the weight of the body rather than trying to use your muscles. In that way the breath can flow in and out quite comfortably.

Where do we keep our hands? I like to keep my right hand on top of the left and allow the thumbs to touch a little bit sometimes. If that becomes a little bit too warm for you, you can move your hands and put them half way. You can even spread your fingers a little bit. So they just sit down there in the lap in a comfortable position. Some people like to put their hands on their knees. That’s fine as well. That can be nice and stable as well. Just be careful when you start to put your hands on your knees, it doesn’t make you start leaning forward. And then your legs might become numb and your breathing won’t be flowing as smoothly as it could be. Hands on the knees is fine or even half way down on the thighs as well is fine.

As far as your eyes are concerned, you can keep your eyes open or you can keep them closed or you can do a bit of both. Most people will meditate with their eyes closed. But also meditating with the eyes open is very, very effective. There’s nothing to stop us to come into the present with the eyes open. In fact, as our practice develops, you’ll be meditating with your eyes open more and more. Especially in our daily life, we have our eyes open most of the time when we are awake. So you can start keeping your eyes open, but eventually they will close down when you become more and more concentrated. – Just lightly close your eyes. As beginners, we often want to see things with our eyes in the meditation, however, meditation is not carried 21 out by the eyes. It’s carried out by the mind. We are trying to see with the mind. – Try to let the eyes go. I know it’s a place where consciousness very often arises. It arises at the eye door. It arises at the ear door. Continuously, over and over again. Consciousness is used to being in these areas of the body process. – So in our practice, we try to resist the urge to use the eyes all the time in our meditation.

That’s the preliminary instruction. You’re setting yourself up, the posture. We want to be able to maintain this sitting for at least 45 minutes. If during the sitting, it becomes extremely painful, of course, you can move your legs a little bit. When I started to sit in meditation, it was extremely painful. I started by lightening an incense stick which burns for 45 minutes. I started sitting for 15 minutes cross legged, and then I moved by putting my leg on the side, and do that for another 15 minutes, and then when that became too painful I put my legs to the other side. And that was the first few months of my meditation practice.

If you find that it is really, really uncomfortable, just stand up. You can stand up for a few minutes and then sit back down again. Just because you are changing postures from sitting to standing to sitting, it doesn’t mean that your meditation has to stop at all. Your meditation can continue in the present moment as you change your body.

We learn to meditate by sitting as still as possible because it’s easier. Once you have the hang on it, we don’t need to meditate in a still sitting position. We can meditate throughout the day in anyone of the four postures, walking, standing, sitting, lying down, and in fact, in any of the other postures we get the body in when we’re doing other activities.

2.3. First stage: Internalizing awareness – letting go of past and future

So let’s have a look at our sitting meditation now with the first step. We have established our body, found a comfortable position to sit in. What’s the first thing we do? We start paying attention to the present moment. This is the beginning of our mind development. We are gathering the mind into the present moment. It likes to wander into the past and future. We are just bringing it back and internalizing our awareness. We do this continuously 22 the first few moments of our meditation sitting. The first minute, at least, this should be your only object. Don’t come into the hall and start immediately watching your breath. You need to establish your awareness in the present moment and you need to internalize your awareness. So our first step is continuously directing the mind to the now. And just hold it with that as the object now. Just being aware of now. Present. Present. Just keep directing the mind bringing it into the center. Again and again. If it wanders off, don’t be upset. We just bring it back and start again. Be aware when thoughts arise of the past – memory, or of the future – planning, and bring yourself back into the present. If your mind goes into the past or future, stop it quickly. Be aware and alert that you’ve just exited meditation and you’re just sitting on the floor in a hall on a mountain, no longer meditating. You’re engaging in your thoughts. You’re no longer present, you’re no longer here. So bring yourself back to the present. Many will find that this is a major part of their meditation practice for the first few days that they are here. – This is the first stage in letting go. We are letting go of the past and future, we are coming into the present.

2.4. Second stage: Feeling body sensation – letting go of the body

Once you’ve been able to do that, then we direct our attention internally. We direct this present moment awareness, we have established in the first minute and bring it inside. We climb inside the body. We direct our awareness to become aware of the whole body as it is sitting on our mat. Do you become aware of how it feels like? What does the sensation of a whole body feel like? Bring your mind in, be actually inside your body. Climb inside it. If you can’t catch the whole body posture of sitting at once, start at the top and know what the top half of your body feels like and then become aware of the bottom half of the body. Become aware if there is something sitting on the mat. There is something sitting on the mat and it’s breathing! So climb inside and feel what it’s like to actually have that sensation of a whole body sitting there. Start from the top, work your way down. You can even move through your body, if that helps. We’re directing our attention to the sensation of the whole mass of the body as it is sitting there.

23 How do you know that you have a body when your eyes are closed? How do you know it’s there? Just examining that. Can you feel that there is something sitting on the mat? You can’t see it when your eyes are closed and you can’t smell it and you’ve stopped thinking about it. Conceptually you can create an image of your body in your mind, so you can perceive the body. We can perceive the body through the eye door. We can perceive the body through the mind door as a concept. We can even smell the body. We can hear it, making sounds. So there’s many different ways to perceive the body. But what we are interested in here, is perceiving the body through the body door itself. Through the skin! Through the internal sensations of the whole thing. We are not looking at the body, we are not hearing the body, smelling or even licking the body. We want to experience the body through the sense door of touch.

So this is the second object of our meditation practice. And we do this for the second minute of each sitting. Some people will experience the sensation of the body as being all around them. Some people will have the experience being aware of the body from some viewpoint up on the shoulders somewhere. We are not trying to picture the body, to create a mind image of the body, of what you think the body looks like when you’re sitting on the mat. That’s not the object we’re doing here. The object is just the sensation of the whole thing as it’s sitting here. It’s a very subtle physical sensation. You can move your mind in and out, up and down. You can move it, you can feel it. This sensation is there. We are observing the whole body.

First, we let go of the past and the future and we stick with the present. Secondly, we let go of the external world and we are focusing on the internal world. This is the second stage of letting go. Our meditation practice is letting go only. How far, how much can you let go of in the present moment. If you’re noticing and identifying that you are attaching with something, let it go. Our practice is only about letting go. The Buddha’s teaching is only about letting go. Letting go of the idea that you have a personality, that you are a self. In fact, enlightenment takes place, when you have completely let go of the sense of self. That is what we are aiming for. First we’re going to let go of the past and future, we are going to let go of the external world, and then we’re going to start to let go of the physical body. And then we are 24 going to let go of the mental states as well. When we have let go of everything, when there’s nothing left to let go of, the mind experiences that which is beyond conditioned realm. It experiences the unconditioned.

2.5. Third stage: Using the breath to maintain awareness

The third stage of our meditation practice is to start paying attention to the breath. We start to become aware that the breath is flowing in through the nostrils, down through the body to the abdomen. The breath is flowing in and the breath is flowing out. We are going to use the breath, that occurs many times a minute, 12 times in and 12 times out, if you are a regular breather. Sometimes it’s faster, sometimes it’s slower. We are going to be using this flow of the breath as a concept to maintain awareness in the present moment. We are using the breath! As a conceptual structure to maintain our awareness in the present moment. What we are really looking to paying attention to, though, is the physical sensations that are created by the breath that flows in and out of the body. This practice is called chatu dhatu bhavana manasikara, which means paying attention to the four elements. The four elements is what makes up this body. This physical mass that is sitting here, it’s a combination of six elements, actually. We are going to use four of them for our meditation practice in the beginning days. We can cover the other elements later. So what we are directing our attention to is the physical sensations created by four of those elements. We normally just refer to them in English as earth, water, fire and air.

2.6. The four elements

The body is made up of these four physical elements. Don’t take those words literally. Don’t think of a handful of earth, a glass of water, or a mouth full of breath. That’s not what we are talking about here. This is very different from what those words mean. So don’t get lost in the translation.

All along the breath path, as the breath flows in and as the breath flows out, various physical sensations will take place. Some of the sensations will be around the nose area, some of them will be around the throat area, or around the heart area, some of them will be down in the abdomen. It’s possible to feel the breath right up through the head and right away through 25 the body down to the legs. The anatomists and physiologist tell us, that the breath is coming from the nose into the lungs and it does come out again without going any further than the lungs. That may well be true. What we’re actually interested in, however, is the sensations created by the breath as it flows in and out. And the physical sensations go further than the lungs. The physical sensations flow right away through the body. In fact, when your lungs expand, your diaphragm gets pushed down and your stomach moves out. So the oxygen exchange is happening in the lungs. The physical sensations that the breath creates are happening throughout the body. And this is our main object of meditation in the first days of practice. The physical sensations that are created by the breath.

These physical sensations are the characteristics of the four elements. They are the manifestation of the four elements. Those four elements in Pali are pruṭhavī, āpa, teja and vāyu. Earth, water, fire and air. We can think about them in various ways.

The earth element is really the element of extension. It’s the element of solidity. Anything that is solid within this mind and body process sitting here, whether the bones or flesh or the ligaments or the skin, they’re all solid things. There is a certain solidity to our body. It’s a base. It’s something real. My one weighs about 90 kg at the moment. It’s a solid mass of stuff. This is just a foundation for the other elements to play in.

There is also the fire element. The fire element is just the element of temperature. This body does have a temperature aspect to it. 37 or 38°. Sometimes it feels very warm, sometimes it feels very cold which may be just a temperature fluctuation of half a degree or so. But the fact that this thing has any temperature aspect to it at all, means that the fire element is there.

There is also the air element which manifests in many different ways. It manifests as the breath and it manifests in other various ways as well. As pressures and tensions, tingling and vibrations. The air element is flowing throughout the body. The air element is not restricting itself to the nose, the lungs and back again. It’s the energies that flow throughout the body. Different traditions will have different names for 26 the air element. In the Chinese tradition it’s known as chi. In the Indian tradition it’s known as prana. In this Pali tradition it’s referred to as vāyu . This is the element of forces. There are those various forces that are happening in the body. It’s the air element that activates the body and moves it from here and there. The solidity and the fire get pushed around by the air element combining together.

These three elements would be completely separate from each other, if there wasn’t for the water element. The water element is the element that combines these things together. The solid base, the temperature and the energies and forces, that are moving throughout the body, are all held together into a unit, compacted into a body that we call mine, my body. So the water element is cohesive. Now just imagine when you are making some bread, you put some flour which is a powder, some salt which is a powder, some yeast which is a powder in a metal bowl and spin them around. So these three ingredients are there but they’re just powder in a bowl. As soon as you start to add some water to it, it starts to come together to a dough, into a solid mass. Well, this is what our body is. It’s a combination of the earth element, the fire element, the air element and the water element.

There’s also the space element, akasa. It’s also there. It’s very subtle. It’s a different type of meditation practice, but it’s there. We are concentrating on the four elements when we are investigating the body.

These four elements can manifest in different ways. They manifest as different physical sensations. An element can either be strong or weak and they are always fluctuating, always flowing.

If the fire element becomes stronger, then the body becomes warm. If the fire element and gets weak, then the body becomes cool. There’s a sensation of coldness. The fire element has a weak aspect and a strong aspect. The other elements are the same as well.

If the earth element manifests in a strong way, it will be manifesting as hardness, roughness and heaviness. It’s like your teeth are hard and solid. Your fingernails are hard and solid. There’s kind of a roughness if you run your hand through your hair if your hair is short. The earth element can also manifest in a weak manner. It can manifest as softness, smoothness and 27 lightness. Touch your lips with your tongue. There is softness there. The earth element has two aspects to it. It can be either weak or strong. How its characteristics are manifesting, will give you different physical sensations. Hardness, roughness, heaviness, softness, smoothness, lightness. The same thing, they are all the earth element and they will be manifesting in your body continuously. Sometimes the body feels hard, sometimes it feels soft, sometimes it feels very heavy, sometimes it feels very light. It’s the earth element playing around.

The air element, which we will be focusing on a lot this week, the breath in particular as it flows in and out and the abdomen as it rises and falls, displays many different physical sensations. If the breath is fast, then the physical sensations will be pushing and pressure and resistance. If the breath is long and smooth and calm, you will get those smooth and comfortable sensations. You’ll feel gliding, you’ll feel flowing. So depending on how you are breathing, different physical sensations will start to manifest. When the air element manifests at full strength, it will appear as forces rising up, from near the buttocks’ area and forcing up your back. Pushing, supporting your whole back. You feel the energy keeping the body erect. If it wasn’t for that air element, the body would just collapse on the floor. It’s the air element constantly flowing up through the back around and up. It’s consistently flowing. Our arms extending and bending, it’s all the air element.

We’ll be watching out for these physical sensations as our meditation unfolds. In fact, this is the main object of our meditation practice. To become aware, to fully understand, to clearly see the physical body. The physical body needs to be let go of. We’ve been attaching and identifying with it too long already. It has caused a lot of troubles when we attach and identify with the body. So this meditation is to allow us to see the body as it really is. We see the nature of the body and will be able to let go the body. Letting go means not identifying with the body.

Our meditation practice will transition. We will start to use the breath. It flows in and it flows out. This is a conceptual framework that we follow. What we are really interested in, however, are the physical sensations created by the breath. I want you to pay particular attention to three areas as the breath is flowing in and flowing out. In particular I want you to pay 28 attention to the nostril area, the area around the upper lip. Can you feel the breath flowing in? Is there a physical sensation of touching? Can you feel the warmth as it comes out, the coolness as it goes in? Can you feel the vibration that is occurring? Vibrating, it’s the air element. Warmth or coolness, that’s the fire element. Touching sensation, that’s the earth element. Can you feel it flowing down through the body? So we are following it all through the body. We are really only interested in the physical sensations created by the breath. We are not interested in the images or little maps, that you create for yourself of the body.

As it flows down to the chest, you feel some rubbing or some gliding. And then I want you all to pay particular attention to the abdomen as it rises and falls. You breathe in, the abdomen rises. There’s a certain physical sensations that occurs there. As the abdomen falls, there’s a certain physical sensation as well. In fact, there are many different physical sensations. Pushing, twisting, pressure, vibration, tingling, throbbing. All those sensations are there for you to pay attention to.

These physical sensations are not the four elements themselves. These physical sensations are the manifestation of the four elements. We are going to be bringing ourselves into the present moment, internalizing our awareness, then we start paying attention to the breath as it flows from the nose to the abdomen, and from the abdomen to the nose. We are using this concept of the breath to get in touch with the physical sensations. And we’re going to do this continuously over and over again.

We can give you an example of the type of knowledge that arises when we start to watch this way. First of all we are looking at a conceptual thing. And then we are looking at physical sensations. And then we will breakthrough and we will see the actual elements themselves. But this doesn’t happen automatically. We will give you an example of the car down there in the carpark. If someone was to ask you, «so what is it that is sitting there in the carpark?» Our first reaction is, «it’s a pick-up, or it’s a Toyota or it’s a car.» That is a conceptual answer. Yes, there is a general thing there that we call a car. If we look a little bit closer, however, we will start to see actually, what we call car is just a conceptual idea. It’s actually made up of car parts. As we try to describe what it is, «well, there is some wheels, there is some 29 doors, there’s a bonnet, there’s a tailgate, there’s an engine». It’s actually not a car that is sitting there. It’s just an arrangement of car parts. Parts have been arranged in a particular way and so it produces this image of car. That’s what we are normally used to dealing with – concepts! We don’t normally deal with ultimate realities. If they keep asking you, «well, what’s really there?» What is really in the carpark? When you really examine what is sitting there in the carpark, you will find out it is just metal, just glass, rubber and plastic. You will see the car in that way. So our perceptions can change in the way that we see things. We are used to see the body as a conceptual thing. As being my body. We are going to start to have a look at it a little bit more closely. We will start to observe, okay, let’s make our mind present, let’s internalize our awareness, and let’s really have a good look and see and find out what this body is. We come to an understanding of the four elements by going through the physical sensations created by the breath. The breath sensations contain all the four elements. The elements change and the way that we can perceive their change is through the physical sensations that make up the body. In fact, the body is nothing other than these physical sensations and our concepts that we paint on top of it. So that’s what is actually happening in real-time. There is the real things, your physical sensations created by the four elements and then there is what you paint on top. Your conceptual notions of yourself, what you believe you are. Whether you believe it’s a man or a woman, or it believes it’s this nationality or that nationality. Whether it believes, it’s a smart person or a stupid person. Whether it believes it’s rich or poor. Funny or serious. It’s painted all these different things on top of it. We’re going to strip off all those concepts that you painted on yourself and we just want to have a look and see actually what the body is. And this is what our meditation practice starts with.

In order for us to break through and really see these elements as they really are, we will need to pay attention continuously to the present moment. Being able to pay attention to the present moment, means we need an object which is continuously there. The breath is such an object. It arises, stays for a while and ceases. So when we begin practicing mindfulness of breathing, we are aware of the breath as it comes in, and we are aware of the breath as it goes out. We are aware at the beginning of the breath, we are aware of the 30 breath as it flows, we are aware of the breath as it finishes. Three things to pay attention to. When it first starts, as it continues and when it finishes. And then there’s a little gap. And then it starts, continues and finishes. And then there’s a little gap. You can pay attention to all of those things.

There are many advantages of watching the abdomen rising and falling. Make an effort to follow the breath down, and follow the breath up. We will do this for the first day of our meditation practice. Keeping ourselves in the present, keeping ourselves internally, following this concept of a breath coming in and out. If we can follow the breath in and out, make the mind continuous, then it starts to stabilize. It starts to concentrate. The concentrated mind allows us to see beyond the physical sensations. We really see the elements themselves. And that is something that you will breakthrough in time. But you will need to be continuous. Continuity is the secret of success in meditation practice.

In the old days, they used to make fire by rubbing two sticks together. If you try to rub two sticks together, you can do it for 10 minutes and stop for five minutes and do it again for 10 minutes. If you do that, you will get very tired and there will be no smoke or even flame, even any kind of fire produced. Because when you’re working and stop, it cools down again. You work and it cools down again. Just stopping and starting. Our meditation practice is exactly the same. You will need to be continuous in your efforts and then eventually you will make some fire. If you can be continues for half an hour, you will be able to make fire. If you start for five minutes and stop for five minutes, you can do that for 30 years and you still never get a fire! The stop and start method doesn’t work, it doesn’t produce any fire. Even after many, many years of practicing. But after just 30 minutes of continuous application, it starts! So continuity is the secret of meditation practice. You will need to resist any urge that the mind has for going at delighting in some kind of objects. Delighting in the past, in the future, in the present at the sense doors. That is when the mind is going out, that is when the sticks have stopped rubbing. To reactivate your sticks, bring your mind back into the present moment and internalize your awareness. Notice every time your mind wanders away from the breath and bring it back as quickly as you can. Do not entertain any thoughts. Do not entertain, «oh, I should be meditating. 31 I just want to think this story out a little bit. Just let that think a little bit and then I will do my meditation.» That is wasting your time here! And this is precious time! Only seven days that we can practice with full intensity.

So please try to maintain your awareness of the breath continuously as it is flowing in and out. We are paying attention right at the beginning.

In fact, you can follow it all the way through and at the end of the inbreath, you can just say, «now», if you want to. Bring yourself back to the present. At the end of every out-breath you can bring yourself back to the present. You can do this over and over again. Be aware it is starting, finishing, now. Exiting, finishing, now. You keep bringing yourself back into the present moment, observing what is exactly there. Not what you’re imaging to be there, not what you like to be there but just seeing what is there over and over again. We are training the mind. We are narrowing the place where we allow it to run. We allow it to run just into certain objects, certain places. We are following the breath as continuously as we can, noting when it goes in, we know that it’s going in. When it’s coming out, we know that it’s coming out. If we notice any physical sensations as we are following the breath, we pay attention to them. We can make a little note of them. ’In, out’, if you feel the expansion in your chest, make a little note to yourself ‘expanding’. If you feel the pushing, make a note to yourself ‘pushing’. This is the real life experience that you are experiencing. This is the real thing. There is actually a physical sensation taking place in the present moment. This is what we want to come to understand. We want to put ourselves in a position, where we can watch so clearly and so closely the present moment, that whatever physical sensation arises, we know it. We know exactly what it is and we see it clearly for what it is. In this way we won’t attach to the body. We will be able to let go of the body.

Normally, the elements will be nicely balanced. 25, 25, 25, 25%. Occasionally one of the elements will become unbalanced. The earth element will become 40%, the other three will be 20, 20, 20%. At that time you will feel that the body becomes hard. There will be some hardness there. So the whole body is becoming hard. Maybe the fire element becomes unbalanced. You will feel warmth. So the four elements are always adjusting in ratios and the four elements are manifesting in the present moment as sensations in your 32 body according to those ratios. We want to come to understand those physical sensations.

We are going to follow the breath that comes in. When it finishes, we know that it’s finished. This is very important. As soon as one breath finishes, tick the box, done. And then follow the next breath. One by one. We don’t want to get ahead of ourselves. We don’t want to be thinking, «I’m going to meditate for two hours now. I’m going to watch the breath, every single one or even for the next 45 minutes». Just try to do it for that breath, that’s occurring right now. Just follow one breath successful, and then follow another breath. Successful of one, follow another breath. Until you start to follow the breath more closely. In the beginning stages it’s all over the place. The breath will be coming in and out, in and out, your mind will be catching it and then wandering away. Try to come back again. Your awareness is not going to be able to follow it, but eventually, you will start following it a little bit. You come back again, lose it. And then, oh, you’ve latched on. You’ve come into the breath a little bit. Your awareness is starting to become internalized with the breath. You’re getting closer and closer to it. You’re coming inside the body. You are starting to experience the inside nature of the body. So different breath, different physical sensations. Short breath – hard punchiness, long breath – smooth and gliding. You can make a note of this phenomena. You can start to understand that the time to breath in, short breath or long breath, will cause different physical sensations. You can start to see that there is some cause and effect happening here in the present moment. You can start to see that the breath is conditioning the body. There is some conditioning going on. It is not so important to pay attention to this now, but if it starts to become clear to you, make a note of that. There is cause and effect happening between the body and the breath. Cause and effect happening between the breath and the mind as well. All three are linked together. Physical sensations, breath and mind. They’re all adjusting. One is the cause, one is effect. Changing and swapping positions who is causing, and who is affecting who. The mind and body process continues to go on day and night. The breath continues to flow in and out regardless of what you think, regardless of who you are. The four elements are the same. Your four elements are the same as my four elements. The same as the four 33 elements outside. The internal elements are the same as the external four elements. This body is just a physical manifestation of your mind state. We will talk about that later as well.

So become aware of just following the breath. I want you to try to follow the breath as closely as you can. From beginning until end. From beginning until end. We follow them from the nose tip, paying attention to the touching sensation. We follow it down to the abdomen. I want you all to follow and chase the breath in and out. If you find that one place is more comfortable than another to watch, especially I want you to be aware of the rising and falling of the abdomen, if you want to watch the breath just there or if you want to watch the breath just at the nose, you can do that for a little bit. See which one feels more comfortable. But try to follow it in and out the whole way and keep your attention and awareness continuously in the present moment. And then the characteristics of those four elements will start to become clearer and clearer. They will only become clear if you have been able to watch the breath, let’s say for five or 10 minutes. We start to be able to continuously watch the breath over and over again without missing and these physical sensations come to life. They start to display themselves quite clearly and then you’ll break through. Instead of seeing a car or car parts, you will break through and you will see metal, plastic, glass and rubber. You will see the actual reality behind the concept of car, behind the concept of breathing, behind the concept of body. You will see actually what is there. And it will surprise you. It will shock you. It will amaze you, that the mind can actually know the body in such away.

In fact, it has been able to do it for a long time already. We just haven’t trained the mind to do that in our societies. We don’t train the mind in this way. We are not taught to observe to look inside the body. Most of our knowledge in our sciences comes from observing things through the eyeball. Whether it’s the external world or whether it’s the body itself. We look through microscopes. Our knowledge arises through the eye door. We see things and then we think about it, and then we develop some theories and it becomes knowledge. It becomes truth. But all this information only comes into through the eye-door. We will be experiencing the body in a very different way that physiologists don’t experience, that anatomists, the 34 doctors don’t experience. Doctors have been trained to examine the body through their eye-door. They have a vast knowledge of the body, that they have managed to accumulate through the eye-door. The eye-door leads to certain kinds of knowledge and types of information but it doesn’t lead to wisdom in that way. Of course, wisdom arises when we notice and know and let go at the eye-door. But that is not what the scientists have done. So we are going to observe the body in a radically different way than scientists observe the body. We’re not interested in looking at protons, neutrons and electrons. We’re not interested in looking at bone marrow. We are not interested in looking at amino acids. All these things have been investigated for a long time and nobody got enlightened from doing so. That’s because they’ve been observing through the eye-door. We’re going to be using the mind door to investigate the body. The first stage is to become aware of the whole body as it is sitting in its posture.

So when we come into the room, we establish our awareness in the present and then we climb inside. So we are deep inside the body and we are watching the breath as it flows in and flows out. Gliding in and gliding out. We are doing that over and over again. This will give us some knowledge about the nature of the mind and body process.

So we have been talking about sitting meditation. This will be enough for us to get started tomorrow morning when we hit the mat at 4:30.

2.7. Walking meditation

I also want to talk about our walking meditation. In fact, let’s all stand up and as you are standing up there, just bring your awareness into the present moment and become aware of the whole body as it is standing there on the mat. See if you can just become aware of the physical sensations on standing. Close your eyes. How do you know that you have a body? Don’t think about it, experience it. Experience the body with the body. Know the body. Put your mind into your left foot. Now put your mind into your right foot. See if you can swap your mind from the left foot to the right foot. How does it feel like? Is there a different physical sensation when the mind is in the foot as when the mind is not in the foot? Can you experience your mind, your awareness, your consciousness jumping from one foot to the other? Do 35 you feel the physical sensations of softness when you are standing on a mat? There are two objects very present. There is the standing posture, that’s one object. And then there is the touching sensation of your feet on the mat. This is standing. Standing and touching. Left foot touching, standing posture, right foot touching, standing posture.

You can move back and forth. If you need to stand up during the meditation practice, you can stand up and become aware of the hole standing posture. You can become aware of the touching sensation of the feet on the mat. You can move your consciousness from your nose, down to your abdomen. Move your mind around inside your body.

We always start our walking meditation with the standing posture. That’s how we start. We become aware, bring our mind into the present, we climb inside the body. We become aware of the whole thing that’s standing there. There is something standing there. It’s breathing. It’s got holes in the side of its head, it hears stuff. It’s got eyes in the front of its head, it sees stuff. Smelling and tasting go on as well. There’s something there. It thinks about itself a lot. In fact, that’s all it thinks about. Its favorite subject, me. It’s been all its day and all its night thinking about its past and future. It’s completely and totally obsessed with itself. But now it’s just standing. Just standing. – Okay, you can sit down now.

During the retreat we are going to alternate between walking and sitting meditation. We do 45 minutes of walking meditation and do 45 minutes of sitting meditation. As I said before, try to join these two sessions together. Try to make them into an hour and a half. One continuous session if possible. When the formal walking meditation takes place, we try to find a place where we can walk from one place to another. We’re walking from A to B, 15 paces long. 10, 15, 20 as space permits. We’re walking from one place to another place, turning around, and walking back again. We are all going to choose a place where we are going to do this for the week. Some of you like to walk in the meditation hall here. That’s possible. There is also places to walk around the Buddha hall. You can walk around the outside of the Buddha hall or you can walk inside the Buddha hall. You can also walk on these sandy areas. You can also use the yoga hall for your walking meditation practice. Find a place where you won’t be disturbed. Many people tell 36 me that they get disturbed by other people walking around them. Find a place where you can lower your eyes and pay attention to your walking meditation. It should be between 10 and 20 steps long. More than this will make your mind wander. Try to keep it to a back-and-forth process. Walking around a circle sometimes just leads the mind wandering and then you end up with a body just walking around and a mind a million miles away.

Just like in the sitting meditation, where the breath is used as concept for maintaining our awareness in the present moment, we are going to be using the steps of the body to lead us to the physical sensations in the body. What I mean by that is, in the sitting meditation, we are using the breath as a concept, in, out, in, out. If we can do that continuously, we start to become aware of the physical sensations in the body. We are using a concept to get back to real objects, the physical body sensations.

We are going to use the walking meditation to do exactly the same thing. In the beginning stages, you can just use two steps. ‘Lifting, placing, lifting, placing’. This is a concept. The foot lifts up and the foot gets placed down. We are walking back and forth. We’re becoming aware of the beginning of the step and the end of the step. Beginning of the step and the end of the step. If we can put our mind into our feet and can follow along with this, the physical sensations in the body will start to become clearer to us.

You can start by doing the two stage walking meditation or we can start by doing the three stage walking meditation. Up to you! We will explain all of them in a few moments. We can also do the one stage walking meditation. Most of the time we will do, what we call the four stage walking meditation practice. ‘Lifting, raising, moving, placing’.

The physical sensations that are produced in the feet, are our object in this meditation practice. This is the most important thing that we’re paying attention to. We’re keeping our mind in the present moment. We’re keeping our mind internally. We are using a conceptual framework to maintain our awareness in the present moment and we are noting and knowing exactly what is going on. At this stage of practice, just the physical sensations produced by walking. They’re all there. All four elements will be manifesting themselves in the feet.

First you become aware of the standing posture. You stand completely 37 still and bring yourself into the present moment and become aware that the whole body is standing and that the feet are touching the floor. In the walking meditation we don’t need to pay attention to the breath. We are paying attention to the present moment physical sensations that are occurring in the feet while we’re moving the feet.

‘Lifting, raising, moving, placing’. You can use these words if they’re helpful to you. The most important thing about the walking meditation is keeping your mind in your feet. Just like in the sitting practice, we are keeping the mind following the breath. In the walking practice, we must keep our mind inside our feet. Specifically, try to keep your awareness on the sole of your foot that is moving. We want to keep our mind in the moving foot at all times. We’re not just walking around with our minds traveling here and there. We are keeping our mind just in the part of the foot that is moving.

I want you to pay particular attention to the beginning and end of each of these movements. You start to lift and it’s finished. Moving – it’s finished. Placing – finished. Each of these stages comes to an end. It starts and it finishes. There’s a present moment event taking place. It starts and it finishes. And then the new event takes place. It starts and finishes. The moment is arising and passing away. Nothing else continues on from that moment. It’s finished. It’s finished. Things are passing away continuously. So pay attention to this, keep your mind in your feet during the walking meditation.

Where do we keep our eyes? Our eyes in our walking meditation should be lowered. We want to keep our eyes looking at about two meters in front of us. We have our eyes closed a little bit. We don’t want to be in complete darkness – you can try that as well, it’s very effective. But we don’t want to have our eyes open so that we can look at other people. We are not going to spend our time looking at other peoples’ bodies. We are not going to walk around looking at the trees or looking at insects or creatures that we’ve never seen before. There is lots of things to look at. But looking doesn’t lead to meditation practice. We want to keep our awareness inside the body as much as we possibly can. We’re not allowing the mind to run out through our eyes. We are keeping all our energy packaged within the body. We are not looking at anybody. If you hear some sound, don’t go following and try to chase it. Don’t go out trying to identify what that sound is. Is that a car or 38 a motor bike? We are not interested in what the sound is. We just note that some hearing occurred and it’s gone. That’s it. You hear a dog bark and then all the stuff you paint on top of that can be minutes’ worth of nonsense. Just from one noise, one sound – hearing occurring. Hearing is very natural. You have holes in your head. There is sounds outside. Hearing occurs. It doesn’t belong to anyone. There’s nobody there that’s hearing. It’s a natural process. Seeing is the same. There’s nobody who sees anything. But the sensitive matter in your eyeballs can detect light and forms, they are out there, it’s functioning, they’re coming together, seeing is occurring. There’s no person there that needs to be a seer. It’s all natural. An impersonal process. Hearing takes place. Seeing takes place. So in our walking meditation this can be very distracting.

So we try to keep our heads lowered, keep our eyes focused on the ground, we are not looking at other people, we hear some sounds, we just disregard it – okay, hearing occurred, finished, no longer interested in.

A good position for our hands in the walking meditation is just in front. Some people like to keep their hands behind. That’s fine as well. You can keep your hands still at the side. So we want to be as still as possible except for the moving parts that we’re paying attention to. The lifting, moving, placing. So the most important thing is to keep your mind inside your feet while you’re doing it.

Some people become frustrated with the walking meditation. They think it’s not working. When I ask them where their mind is, they say, «what do you mean?» You can’t follow the breath unless your mind is following the breath. You can’t do the walking meditation unless your mind is in your feet. This is where we see the sensations taking place. There is all kinds of sensations happening in the foot. As we lift the foot up, there is one type of sensation. We push the foot forward, there’s another type of sensation. As we place the foot down, there’s another type of sensation. In fact, there is five or six different sensations in each one. Lightness, vibration, softness, pushing, hardness – all there. You can feel them as you do the practice and it will start to unfold.

To give you a demonstration: We stand, we start, bringing ourselves into the present moment, bringing ourselves internal, establish our awareness 39 in the feet, left side, right side, left side, right side, lower the head, open the eyes a little bit so that the light comes in, make a note ‘seeing’ is occurring, and then when you lift your heel have your mind really right in your foot, ‘lifting’, stops, ‘moving’, stops, ‘placing’, stops. It’s really, really important that you have gaps between these three stages. There needs to be a definite stop. There needs to be a lifting. Stop. ‘Moving’. Stop. ‘Placing’. Stop. ‘Standing, standing’. Bring yourself into the full body again. And then when you turn around, ‘lifting, turning, placing’. You’re coming into still again. Standing is taking place. ‘Standing, standing’. And off you go again. 10 steps or 15 steps, back-and-forth, keeping your mind in the present moment, keeping your mind inside the body.

Looking out for physical sensations as they are arising and passing away. The most important thing, keep your mind in the present, keep your mind internal, keep your mind in your feet, when you are doing the walking meditation practice. Make sure there are gaps between the three stages of the walking practice. You need to be able to see the arising and passing. Arising and passing. Arising and passing. Doing a step as you normally walk, there is no breakup. There is no arising and passing away. The sensations will be shifting and changing too rapidly for your mind to be able to catch up to them. So we need to slow down with the walking meditation. We are walking relatively slowly. In particular, the last 20 or 30 minutes of the walking meditation should be much slower than the first 10 or 15 minutes. The first 10 or 15 minutes you establish some rhythm. You should try to be continuous in the rhythm like a watch. ‘Lifting, moving, placing, lifting, moving, placing, lifting, moving, placing, lifting, moving, placing, lifting, moving, placing’. So the mind gets a bit into a rhythm and starts to become aware and contained in itself.

In the beginning stages you will find it quite boring. You won’t be making much sense of it. But once it starts to work, it really works well. For many newcomers to meditation, walking meditation gives them the results before the sitting meditation. So don’t think that the walking meditation is somehow secondary. Many people had some wonderful, deep and profound insights, life changing insights on the walking path in this monastery. Just by walking and paying attention you can learn a lot about the mind and the 40 body process. You can learn a lot about cause and effect.

Try to perform the turning around efficiently. When you hear the bell at the end of the walking meditation practice, walk slowly to the meditation hall. It should be a slow and gradual transition from the walking path into your seat. There shouldn’t be any gaps of unmindfulness to occur. We want to be continuous with our awareness.

You start to see things that you normally don’t see. You start to see weird sensations in the feet. If you are new to walking meditation, I suggest that you walk on a hard surface for the first few days. Walk inside the hall here. Walking on the sand may be a little bit tricky for the first stages of the walking meditation. We also do walking meditation, when we move around the monastery. When you are moving from this hall to the dining hall or when you are moving from the dining hall to your dorm. Try to be aware of the walking posture as well. There’s a whole thing that’s walking. Try to keep your awareness internalized. You can pay attention to the touching of your feet on the floor if you like. No shoes will be helpful for this. This is something I should mention. During the walking meditation we should not use shoes, no flip-flops, no rubber sandals or anything else. We use just our bare feet.

So we need to activate our awareness in the present moment, bring our awareness inside the body and start paying attention to the physical sensations that are occurring, using the concepts of the in- and out-breath, using the concepts of lifting, moving, placing, we can bring our mind into an experience of nature. Into an experience of reality.

I want you all to pay very much attention making your walking meditation smooth and continuous. Just like the clock. Tic-tic-tic-tic-tic-tic. This happens very smooth and continuously. So should our walking meditation be. Lifting, moving, placing, lifting, moving, placing. Try to get yourself into a rhythm.

Of course, there is going to be thoughts coming up. There are two types of thoughts. Two ways that we can deal with thoughts that happen on the walking meditation path. Some thoughts are just going to be little ones, that just kind of bubble up and don’t lead anywhere. You just have a thought about something and then it’s gone again. When those kind of thoughts 41 happen, you can just note it. Thinking is occurring. And then continue with your walking practice. If you find that thoughts come up and turn into a bit of a story, if you find that you are just walking around, lifting, moving, placing, but your mind is thinking about other things then you need to stop. You need to stop and stand still and become quiet for a moment. And then start again. During the first few days this may happen very often.

For a warm up you can just stand on one foot. Just lift one foot up, keep your awareness in the front of the foot, in the middle of the foot, and than just drag it back keeping your mind inside your foot. And then push it forward. And pull and push. Keeping your mind inside. Can you feel the physical sensations on the bottom of the foot? On the sole of the foot? There is some vibrations going on there. Keep your mind in your foot while you’re pushing it forward. It is really a push. We say moving, but it’s really pushing the foot through. Feel the friction and the resistance that’s there if you push and pull your foot backwards and forwards. Like you’re pushing it through water.

Sometimes our walking meditation feels like we are on cross country skis or we are ice skating. We are really pushing the foot and pulling the foot. Try to catch that physical sensation there on the bottom of the foot. It’s the physical sensation which is the object of our meditation. That is what we follow. That physical vibration on the bottom of the foot.

It may take some time to get used to it. You’re certainly used to walking. But you’re not used to putting your mind in your feet. The mind normally goes out to enjoy the sensual pleasures. Something delightful through the eye, ear, nose, tongue or body door. Something to think about. We’re keeping the mind inside the body and we’re paying attention to the physical sensations. If you like, before you start the walking meditation practice, just warm your feet in this way up for your walking meditation. Push, pull, push, pull. About 10 times on each foot. Just kind of warm-up your awareness for that physical sensation. And then once you have warmed it up, try doing your walking practice and you will find, that you will be able to follow along a lot easier.

There’s a few other things. No shoes when we do the walking meditation. We don’t need to lift up the feet high either and we are not walking one 42 foot in front of each other either. We’re not on a catwalk in kind of some balancing act. Just the normal way that you walk, the normal height that you walk. In fact, if you keep your feet lower to the floor, you will have a better balance.

This is how we practice the walking meditation. The walking meditation instructions will be updated almost daily and we will go further and further and so will be the sitting meditation practice.

3. Day 1, morning

3.1. General outline

This morning we’re going to talk about Vipassana and give you a general outline about what we’re doing here this week. We’ve introduced the practice last night giving you first initial mediation instructions, putting the mind into the present moment, internalizing your awareness and paying attention to the breath as it comes in and out of the body. In particular, we are paying attention to the physical sensations produced by the breath as the breath flows in and out of the body

This morning we’re going to look at Vipassana. We said last night «vi» is an intensifying prefix, «passana» means to see. So to see clearly. To see things as they really are, that’s what Vipassana means.

The ground of Vipassana is satipatthana practice. Vipassana starts to arise when we practice satipatthana or activating our awareness on the four foundations of mindfulness. Those four foundations are the physical sensations in the body, feelings – either pleasant or unpleasant – emotional states and the fourth one is reaction or thoughts or identification if you like.

All Vipassana systems take these four foundations of mindfulness as their base. Sometimes the techniques can be slightly different but they’re all establishing awareness in the present moment using our own mind and body 44 process as the objects of our observation. So the purpose of Vipassana is to see things as they really are, to see the mind and body process in the present moment as impermanent, unsatisfactory and non-self.

The duty of this practice is to destroy defilements at the six sense doors. Once your awareness and wisdom can be activated continuously in the present moment, we move from just observing the body door or selected objects and we start to broaden our awareness out to the six sense doors. The eye door, the ear door, the nose door, the tongue door, the body door, that we’re working with at the moment, and the mind door. These six sense doors. We’ll be able to note, know and let go at these six sense doors.

The purpose is to first of all start to wiggle free of this sense of self that we’ve developed over a period of time moment after moment, after moment of being unaware of what’s actually going on in the present moment, allowing craving for being to enter into the present moment, allowing craving to infiltrate the field of awareness. What happens is that craving for being subjectifies that moment. It becomes a moment where things are taken as me, mine and I. It becomes a moment where duality is created. There’s a me and there is the external world and all other people going on around it. And this happens very naturally and continuously. It happens without us thinking about it. It’s been going on since we were borne. It’s happening to everyone unless, of course, they’ve done the practice, seen it happening for them in real time and they’ve been able to follow the advice, the strategy given by the Buddha in uprooting this sense of self, removing this sense of self. We’ll be going into this subjectivity and how it arises as the retreat goes on. But just know that the practice or the duty of the practice is to destroy defilement, destroy the liking and disliking, destroy the attachment and aversion that is arising at the six sense bases continuously. The ultimate result of our Vipassana practice is the full removal of dukkha, the full understanding of dukkha, which allows us to understand the nature of craving and see the cessation of craving and that the path is fulfilled.

So we’re going to be using some various tools on this journey for understanding the sense of self and removing the sense of self. First of all we’ll be collecting some information on this sutta-maya pañña, the type of knowledge which arises from information. Somebody gives you some information 45 and you’ll know something about it, something about the object or something about the subject. Secondly, we use also a bit of thinking, this is citta-maya pañña, the type of wisdom that arises through thinking. Not the full understanding of an object – there are various levels of understanding of things. The third type of wisdom that arises is the wisdom that arises from pañña, from bhavana, bhavana-maya pañña. This is the wisdom that arises intuitively. We’re going to use all three of these types of wisdom. They all have different levels.

If I was going to tell you about my parents’ house, what it looks like, then you’ll have some information. You’ll understand to a certain degree of what type of house they live in. It won’t be very clear but you’ll have some understanding. That’s the first layer, the first level of understanding something. Secondly, we normally think about things. If I tell you about my parents’ house and then you start to think about it. You start to analyze it. You may come to a bit more of a clearer picture what this thing is, what this house is my parents are living in. Still, you wouldn’t fully imagine exactly how it looks like. You don’t know exactly how my parents’ house is like. You have never been there. You have never really examined it. You can look at it on the map and get all kinds of information. Various people can tell you about what my parents’ house looks like. You can even have some photos of how my parents’ house looks like. There are many different ways of collecting information and trying to discover what it is. But until you have actually been to my parents’ house, you don’t actually know what it truly is.

And it’s the same with the meditation practice. We don’t fully understand the nature of the mind and the body process simply by reading about it, reading about meditation. We won’t understand the mind and body process through thinking about it. Thinking is actually an object of wisdom. Thinking about something doesn’t lead us to wisdom. Thinking is an object of wisdom. Finally we get through all the information and all the thinking, we can put that all aside and we can experience our own mind and body process through our own meditation practice. That’s when we come to a true understanding about the nature of the mind and body process – this mind and body process, that’s going on here. We are not so interested in other people’s mind and body processes. We’re interested in investigating this one here. We’re interested in investigating what we know as nama-rupa. Nama 46 means the mind, rupa means the matter. Mind and matter. It’s a mind and matter process that we’ve painted in our perception, in our thinking, so we get a conceptual idea about what it actually is. However, our concepts don’t truly cover the nature of our mind and body process. So this week, we’re going to be investigating this mind and body process. Essentially the mind and body process are in a vortex, dependent upon each other. When the mind arises, the body also arises. When the body arises, the mind also arises. So these things are locked together in a vortex dependently conditioning each other. We’re going to be looking into this.

Last night we talked about the nature of the body, the four elements. The elements of extension, temperature, movement and cohesion. These four elements joining together making this physical body. And then there is a mind as well. There is a mind which has feelings, it has various perceptions, various thoughts about it – primarily those three things are joined together in the mind. And then there is consciousness.

Consciousness is that which knows the mind and body process. The mind and body process are spinning, are dependent on each other. Consciousness is like a vessel that allows these things to arise and pass away. Consciousness is also arising and passing away. In fact, the body, the mind and consciousness – the five aggregates are arising and passing away every single moment. Moment after moment. They’re arising and passing away at the six sense bases. At these six doors the five aggregates are manifesting. There will be a physical component to our experience, there will be a feeling component to our experience, there will be perceptions and recognitions about what is going on, there will be some thought, liking and disliking and subjectification about the experience that’s going on in the present moment. Our experience which is the experience of consciousness is just simply mind and matter. It doesn’t belong to anybody. It doesn’t have an owner. It’s a mental and physical phenomena arising and passing away according to their conditioning, arising and passing away according to the law of dependent arising. And we’ll be talking more on this as the week goes on.

Essentially what we’re doing in our Vipassana meditation practice is observing this mind and body process. Consciousness which is just the 47 knowing, it’s just knowing, it knows things. That’s its only function. It’s not yours, it’s not you! You’re not the consciousness and the consciousness does not belong to you. It’s function is to know things. When presented with something, it knows it. Depending on what factors are surrounding consciousness it’ll know in a particular way. If our consciousness is surrounded by helpful mental factors, then we’ll start to see things as they really are. When consciousness is surrounded by hindrances, mental states that cloud the mind and don’t allow us to see things clearly, then that will be our experience. So our meditation practice is to develop certain mental factors, so that we can surround the knowing with able bodied workers so that they can note and know exactly what is going on in the present moment.

So we’ll start to dissect our sense experience. First we’ll do it by me talking to you and then we’ll start to realize for ourselves in our practice. We’ll go through a few different exercises.

I’ve said last night that the present moment is defined as mind and matter which is arising independent of desire. This is what nama-rupa is. Nama-rupa arising independent of desire. Mind and matter, when it arises in its natural state, when it is not infected by craving, when it is not infected by craving for being, when it’s not under the illusion of a self trying to become something, it’s not trying to be anything, it’s not interested in a self or becoming an ego or developing more sense of I, when the mind and body process drops this behavior, we start to experience some freedom. We start to experience the results of Vipassana practice. We start to experience the world which is beyond defilement, beyond craving arising in the present moment. We’ll be able to see this for ourselves. This is a well tested meditation technique that’s been practiced for a very long time, many, many centuries. In fact for 26 centuries people have been practicing this meditation technique realizing the benefits of this meditation technique. I hope you all have a good opportunity to really practice this week and to realize the benefits of this practice.

As we’re practicing in this way, not only do we want to understand what is the content of our mind, not only do we want to understand the physical sensations in the body. That’s the individual characteristics of things. We know when the mind is happy, we know when the mind is feeling greedy or 48 when it’s feeling some aversion. We know when the mind is starting to calm down and become still. We know when the mind is becoming agitated. These are the individual characteristics that arise and pass away. This is mental and physical phenomena arising and passing away in the present moment. It’s one thing to understand these. It’s one thing to understand all the different content but we don’t want to get stuck in content. Our Vipassana practice goes far beyond the contents of our body and mind process.

What we’re looking at is the structure and the nature of the mind and body process. There are many thoughts that will arise and pass away. There will be many different subjects, they’ll be arising and passing away on the past, arising and passing into the future. Arising and passing away thinking, imagining, reflecting – all kinds of mental activities will be going on. These are all independent events but they are all joined together. They all have one common characteristic, or should we say they have three common characteristics. When we look at them from a structural point of view, they are all impermanent. It doesn’t matter what the content is, it arises and passes away. All the content, all the mind and body processes are also dukkha. We’ll be using this word this week, dukkha, normally translated as suffering or unsatisfactoriness. It’s a word the Buddha used to describe the unsatisfactory nature of the mind and body process when it’s under the illusion of a self. When the mind and body process has chosen to believe it is somebody, when the mind and body process has become subjectified. And this is called dukkha. The Buddha’s term for it was pancha uppadhana kandha vidukkha. The five aggregates affected by clinging or attachment is dukkha.

So we’ll be investigating this and seeing that these mind states, as different as they may be, all share three common characteristics: they’re impermanent, they’re relatively unsatisfactory and they’re also non-self. These mind processes that arise and pass away, the physical body that arises and passes away, don’t belong to anybody. It’s all happening by itself. In fact, there is an intricate law of nature that combines things together, that combines the mind and body together, causes and effects together, to produce this result, this ongoing flow, this ongoing manifestation of mind and body process in the present moment. It’s completely out of control.

So, impermanence, dukkha and non-self of all conditioned phenomena 49 is what we want to get to in our Vipassana practice. At the moment we’ll start to watch the body, come to terms with that, then we’ll start to have a look at the mind, come to terms with that. We’ll start to see that sometimes the body is the cause, sometimes it’s an effect. Sometimes the mind is a cause, sometimes the mind is an effect. All these things, causes and effect, mind and body, all are subject to the same three characteristics. They are all impermanent, they’re all subject to change, they’re unstable, they’re arising and passing away. They’re being used as an object in which craving can enter upon and develop a sense of me. They are the matrix, these mental and physical phenomena. They are not you! They arise and pass away so rapidly that you can’t possibly identify as being you once you’ve seen them. You’ll know that that’s not you. That’s not me. I’m not that. And definitely not that. You’ll start to see that there is nobody there. Nobody in the mind and body process! There’s no experiencer! There’s lots of experiencing. Hearing is occurring but there is no hearer. Seeing is occurring but there is no seer. Thoughts arise and pass away but there is nobody who is thinking them. There is no thinker there. It’s all a dependently arisen, conditioned matrix, that’s arising and passing away. Unfortunately, it has been affected by craving to be. This very strong desire to become has infected the mind and body process. Each experience is taken as an experience for me, it’s taken as being mine. This is happening to me. This is where I was born, these are my parents. The whole world is subjectified with me at the center. It’s me, and everything else is going around. We’ve created a duality.

Luckily for us, there is a way out of this. We need to be able to see the structure of our sense experience. We need to understand that it’s all impermanent. We need to see that this is an unsatisfactory state of affairs. This is an unsatisfactory place, we got ourselves in. When we see the arising and passing away of mental and physical phenomena, you’ll come to understand that this is indeed quite an unsatisfactory situation. You’ll come to understand why the Buddha called this dukkha. You’ll understand that this mind and body process has been arising and passing away for a very, very, very long time. And it will continue to do so, unless something is done about it. Unless it can be broken through and seen as it really is. And that’s the purpose of our Vipassana practice. To break through and see that this mind and 50 body process doesn’t actually belong to anyone. It’s fueled by its old karmic intentions. Old karmic intentions producing their resultants. That’s what this mind and body is. Effectively resultants coming from old karma manifesting in the present moment believing that they are somebody. And then, a new karmic resultant has the opportunity to arise and pass away. And then a new one. And then a new one arises and passes away. It’s incessant! It’s continuous! There are very little gaps. Impermanence is hidden from us by what is known as santati or continuity. We can’t see the gaps, just like when we’re watching a film, we don’t see the individual frames of the film. We see the movie. Actually that movie is made of each discrete individual events and so is our life made up of exactly this at the six sense doors arising and passing away so rapidly that we actually never see the frames. We only see the movie and the movie is my life. The movie is about me.

You’ll notice this week that you spend a lot of time thinking about yourself. This is not because of the retreat. This is how it normally is. We’re just noticing it for the first time perhaps. You’ll see that this thing continuously, incessantly thinks about itself. It’s completely obsessed with itself. It can’t think of anything else to think about. It loves to think about itself. Reminisces about the past or the traumas of the past or the worries of the past. Or it’s interested in what its plans are going to be, how it’s going to become, what it’s going to manifest as. It loves to think about that stuff. Diligently planning every detail of where it’s going to be and what it’s going to become. If it’s not doing those things then it’s engaging and indulging in enjoyment and delight in sensual pleasures finding little things for it to enjoy. It finds little nice things to look at, pleasant things to listen to, nice things to smell and taste. When those things don’t interest it anymore, it goes and finds some new things. This is what this mind and body is doing. Constantly reacting to pleasant feeling and unpleasant feeling. Dukkha is hidden from us by the body posture. By simply not paying attention to the body, not paying attention to the posture, we don’t see the nature of dukkha. Dukkha is arising in this mind and body process continuously. Just try holding your body still for an hour. Any posture, it doesn’t matter, sitting, standing, walking or lying down. Try to do all, try to do one for an hour and see what happens to the body. See if you can feel any unpleasant sensations 51 arising in the body. It’s continuously arising. This thing is a manifestation of unpleasant physical sensations. That’s why we have to keep moving it. That’s why we have to constantly transition between these four different postures. Walking, standing, sitting and lying down. Because the dukkha, the painfulness, just keeps coming. Hold it like this for while. It becomes too much, you have to move your leg. You sit down, you have to stand up. Even when you’ve been lying down, even that becomes uncomfortable. You have to sit up, you have to stand up, you have to walk a little bit. If you have been walking, you have to sit down again. Constantly transitioning between these four postures. This is what hides the nature of dukkha from us. By not paying attention to our posture. When we don’t see the posture, when we don’t internalize our awareness in the present moment, we don’t see what’s happening. We just think we’re moving our shoulders, just make ourselves a little more comfortable, lean a little bit, do this, lean that way, find a wall to lean on and slumping our shoulders. Finding any kind of comfortable position, see how long you can keep it and then, dukkha manifesting. You have to move again! Constantly moving.

The third characteristic of non-self is hidden by compactness or ghana- saññā, perception of compactness. It appears like this mind and body process is all joined together. It’s all pacted. We can’t see beyond it. Just like the car down their in the car park. We don’t see beyond «car». It’s compacted. We just see one thing. «Car». That’s it. We don’t bother to investigate. It is actually different car parts. Actually, it’s only rubber, glass, metal and plastic. We don’t investigate that. We don’t see that. We don’t see the conceptual objects and don’t see it in our own mind and body process. The fact that things are separated is hidden from us because of this swiftly, constantly flowing river. There is no gaps in it. Compacted together.

So these three characteristics of our structural experience is what Vipassana practice is all about. You’ll intuitively know impermanence, dukkha and non-self. You’ll know them as dependent arisen and conditioned. When we don’t take any as self then we are starting to free the mind. That’s the real purpose of our meditation practice. Once we’ve removed the concept of personality, of this distorted view of individuality, we’ll understand that this is actually the seed of all our problems. This is where our problems come from. 52 You’ll start to notice that actually when I’m being really selfish and I have a very strong sense of self, there is quite a lot of dukkha associated with that. Lots of self, lots of dukkha. Reduce your sense of self, reduce your dukkha. A little bit of self, a little bit of dukkha. No self, no dukkha. The cessation of dukkha is completed when the sense of self is fully removed. Dukkha is dependent on me, mine and I. Dependent on this sense of self arising in the present moment. Our conceptions of «I am» are based upon this present moment experience continuously multiplying moment after moment after moment. It becomes so continuous, it flows so uninterruptedly, so mechanically that we don’t actually see what’s going on. Luckily 26 centuries ago the Buddha saw what was going on and he was able to teach what he came to know for himself. Not only that people that he taught were also able to understand the nature of reality and they also became enlightened beings. And so this tradition has passed down to us. There are still people on the planet who are enlightened. They had followed the teaching and completed the training. I have met them, enlightened beings following the teaching. This is our opportunity to practice this wonderful teaching, to realize the true nature of the mind and body process, to stop identifying with it. The stuff is still going to be arising. Your old karma is still going to manifest in this live. Mind and body process will still keep bubbling away, but the more you can remove your sense of self, the more pleasant you’ll find the whole experience. If you can completely remove your sense of self from nature, from this mind and body process that is arising and passing away, then you’ll have found a state of freedom. A state of peace. A state of comfort. A state of great bliss. A state of loving kindness and compassion for other beings. And this is where our Vipassana practice is heading.

You will need to obtain a level of concentration, you will need to be mindful continuously from moment to moment. It’s through continuous mindfulness, continuous attention to what is actually going on in the present moment that concentration arises. If we can actively note what’s going on and we do that continuously, we are aware, we’re witnessing, observing, we’re paying attention but we’re not interfering with what’s going on. We’re just watching. We are the detached watcher. Just being attentive observing. Witnessing is taking place. This is the power of mindfulness and wisdom. 53 We’ll be talking more about them as the week goes on.

So we are establishing our awareness in the present moment, we are activating our awareness continuously. In the beginning stages of the practice you’ll need to do this very often. Your mind will wander here and there. You go into the past and future thinking about various things. You will need to reactivate your awareness and bring it back into the present and know what is the object of consciousness. Keep bringing your awareness back into the present and seeing what’s there. That’s what our practice is all about. If you can do this continuously, keep bringing yourself back to the present, keep bringing yourself back, what happens is that the mind stabilizes in this mode of awareness. In the beginning stages that’s difficult just to get into it for a few seconds, just to get into this awareness, that you’ll be there and that you’re present with what’s going on. And then your mind will run away again. You’ll follow the breath a little bit, you can be there with it and then your mind will run away again. This is very normal. Anyone who has trained a dog will know. You have to train it. It will take some patience, it will take some effort but eventually the dog understands that it has to go and piddle outside. You bring it in, it starts to piddle, you put it outside again. It comes back inside, it gets comfortable, it starts a little piddle, you take it outside and it does it out there. Eventually it knows that it has to go outside to go to the toilet. In our meditation practice as well, if we continuously keep averting our intention and the awareness to the present moment, our mind starts to learn, starting to train our mind to come back into the present. At the beginning it’s difficult, but after a while, we get used to it.

3.2. Noting, Knowing, Letting go

We activate our awareness. What’s there? We note it! When I say «we note it» that means, we just make a recognition in our mind. And this is what’s there. Just that! We are just noting it.

The second part of our operation is, we know the object. We note what’s there and then we know it. We know it in a very special way. We know it as an object. We see it for what it actually is. We know it as an independent, discrete event that’s occurring. It’s either a mental event or it’s a physical event. It’s impermanent, we know it’s arisen, it’s there, we watch it and it 54 passes away. We understand the nature of it. This is a conditioned, dependently arisen object, it’s out of control. It has arisen when its conditions are in place and it has passed away when those conditions are no longer there. It’s an independent, dependently arisen, conditioned mental or physical phenomena. It has probably been subjectified. It has probably been identified as being me and mine. And so dukkha arises in that moment. If our awareness can be sharp enough, if we can note and know the object so that craving for being doesn’t have a chance to enter into the moment, then that’s a moment of freedom. That’s a moment of cessation of dukkha. We can free the mind in that moment.

So what we do is we note whatever’s there, we know it – by knowing I mean we step back from it, disengage from it, stop identifying with it, we see it just as it is, put a little fence around it, if you like, or build a wall around it or put it up on a high shelf, there it is, it’s not me, it’s not mine, it’s not I. It could be «hearing». It’s not «I am hearing». There is some hearing occurring. When we look at our physical sensations, normally, we look at it from a subjective point of view. «My painful knee». There is some physical sensations that is there. That’s all it is. There is some unpleasantness that’s there, that’s all it is. There is a physical object, there is a mental object and there is a subjectification of that. My painful knee. Three things are going on there. We can note them. We can note and know them so that our mind doesn’t get trapped, that it doesn’t get engaged, that it doesn’t get immured with the object and it passes away. This is how the letting go process takes place in the present moment.

We activate our awareness, we note what’s there, we step back from it, not engaging with it in any way, we’re not thinking about it or analyzing it, we are just stepping back from it and then we watch it pass away. It arises, we note it, we step back and it passes away. It arises, we note it, we step back and it passes away. We do this over and over and over again. This is what our meditation practice is all about. Freeing the mind, freeing consciousness from the mind. Freeing consciousness from the mind and body process. Consciousness, which is like a bowl; mind and body are like the fruit that is sitting in the bowl. Without a bowl the fruit can’t have a sit. You can’t have a bowl that is just empty. It’s got to have something in it. So they’re 55 in kind of a relationship, this bowl and this fruit. They have to go together. Consciousness is the bowl that allows the fruit to be there. The fruit can only be there if there’s a consciousness. So they are in this symbiotic relationship causing and effecting each other. Mind and body sometimes is the cause of consciousness. Consciousness is sometimes the cause of mind and body. They are arising and passing away together. We need to be able to see this in real-time.

To do this we need to be able to note and know and let go. Note, know and let go. Note, know and let go. Note, know and let go. And we need to do it continuously. We need to do it rapidly. The more rapidly you can do the practice, the quicker you’re letting go will take place. You will be able to see things more and more clearly. In the beginning it takes a lot of effort to put forth this noting, doing this noting, being aware of exactly what is the content of your consciousness right now. What’s happening now: Is it hearing? Is it seeing? Is it smelling? Is it tasting? What is it now? What is happening now? Is it hearing? Is it seeing? Smelling? Tasting? Touching? The five sense doors are constantly stimulated by the environment. If there are sounds, hearing occurs. If there are visible forms, seeing occurs. The body is touching this mat, touching is occurring! The body is feeling a little bit warm, warmth is occurring there! Vibration is there. These physical and mental phenomena are going on all over the place continuously arising and passing away. If we are aware in the present moment, we can block craving from entering the moment and there is a moment of freedom.

If we’re unaware of the moment, then craving will enter the moment and cause, what the Buddha called dukkha, this unsatisfactory state of affairs, where the mind and body process have become subjectified. They think they are somebody. Trapped! We are trapped in a sense of self. We are trapped in the matrix. Luckily for us, if we can note and know and let go and keep noting and keep noting and keep noting, moment after moment after moment, moment after moment, what happens, is this mode of perception stabilizes. The mind becomes concentrated and starts to see things in this mode more frequently, more commonly, more often, continuously. The curtain opens and we start to see what is really going on in the present moment. We see things as they really are. The letting go mechanism takes place and 56 we are free in that moment. All we have to do is extend that moment out, keep extending our awareness in the present, keep extending our wisdom, which de-identifies with things. Being aware in the present moment is just not enough. Awareness will take us to the present and we’ll know what’s there but we need wisdom as well. Wisdom allows not to get engaged with the object. We note it and we are right there with it. Wisdom is that which steps back. So we are noting and we are knowing. The result of this is letting go. We are noting, knowing, letting go. Whatever physical phenomena is arising in the body, make a note of it. Whatever mental phenomena is arising, make a note of it. Whether it’s an emotional state or a judging state or complaining state or if it’s pleasantness or if it’s unpleasantness or if it’s hot or if it’s tired, if it’s hungry, what ever is going on. Vipassana meditation is paying attention to just what is. We are not trying to create anything special. We are trying to observe nature as it bubbles up. We want to see it as it comes up completely undisturbed. We are not trying to manipulate the mind and body process. We are trying to let it go. We are trying to completely and totally detach from it, so it can just do its thing without the sense of me being in there.

When you experience that for yourself, you will experience a very large amount of bliss, you will be very happy, very pleased and very free. This is where our meditation practice goes.

We are not having reactions to the objects, we are not trying to like or dislike them. We are just allowing them to arise and pass away. We are not judging things as being good or bad. We are not comparing things. The mind often likes to compare. It likes to go into the past. To think about how it was then and how it is now. It likes to compare with the future. How much better it’s going to be in the future compared to what it is now.

So just be aware of whatever is occurring without any entanglements. We are going to follow the breath and use that as a conceptual framework to keep us in the present as we observe what is going on. Watch things as they occur. As our mindfulness gradually becomes more constant, more continuous and more powerful, the mind starts to stabilize in various levels, in various stages. Depending on the stage of stability, on the level of concentration you will see things as they really are up to that level. The more you can let 57 go of, the more stable your awareness will become. So it will become concentrated. The mind will enter a concentrated state of samadhi. It will be able to see things as they really are.

The most important thing to be aware of is whatever object is arising in the moment. That’s the most important thing to note. If you are unsure of what you need to be noting, whatever is there is the answer. Whatever is arising that’s what we pay attention to. We are not trying to create any special object. Just whatever is there. Activate your awareness in the present. What’s there? What are you thinking about? What is your emotional state? Are you feeling happy? Is there pleasantness in the moment or is there unpleasantness in the moment? Is there some physical sensations occurring in the moment? Is there any emotional state occurring? Are you looping on something? Are you thinking about something? Are you becoming angry about something? Are you disliking something? Have a look at that! Maybe you’re becoming happy about something.

Our mindfulness meditation is the practice of non-reaction. We are not reacting, we are not judging. Mindfulness is a process which is not judging. You are not calling things as good or bad. That is a reaction of the mind. Things are as they are! They are perfectly fine! Of course, we can make trouble by saying this is good or this is bad. Things are as they are. So our practice is just to be aware of whatever is occurring.

We can listen to something. We can hear those insects in the background there. We can listen. That involves somebody who is listening. Hearing doesn’t involve anybody. Hearing is occurring. Hearing is a natural state. There is holes in your head, there is sound outside. Ear drum and sound meeting together, ear consciousness arising. It doesn’t belong to anyone. It’s not you. It’s not yours.

Why are you identifying with it? Why are you becoming upset with it? «Oh, that sound is happening to me!» Hmm, you have appropriated that sound! You are unable to note it in the present moment, ’hearing, hearing’, that is what is actually happening right now. Hearing process is activated. So we are aware that hearing is occurring. When we understand it as just hearing, hearing is just hearing. It’s not «I am hearing something» or «I am listening». When we can see it as just hearing, only that, then we have freed 58 the mind from the subjectivity that we have become involved with – if we can note and know fast enough, if we can keep noting continuously to block this sense of self from getting into the sense perception process.

It is constantly trying to enter. Craving is constantly there, swirling like a cloud in our present moment experience. It wants to be. This is its very nature. Craving really, really wants to be somebody. It really wants to be something. Think about it! It is all you are thinking about. «I want to be this, I want to study this, I want to study that, I want to be this person, I want to be that, I want to have this, I want to have that job title, this car, this amount of money.» It wants to be. It doesn’t matter, unfortunately for us, it doesn’t matter what it wants to be. It attaches to both pleasant and unpleasant experiences. It gains the sense of self from the pleasant experiences, «I am happy, this is great», and it gains a sense of self from the unpleasant experiences. «This is awful, what am I doing here».

All of those thoughts, when they are unseen, when we are unmindful of them, when we haven’t been able to note and know in the present moment exactly what that mind state is, we get sucked into it! We get sucked into it and start identifying with it. The pleasantness is no longer just pleasantness. It is pleasantness for me. The unpleasantness, it’s just unpleasantness. Oh, there is some unpleasantness arising. If we note it and know it, we can free our mind from that unpleasantness. If we don’t see it fast enough, we will get sucked into it. Absorbed into it. That unpleasantness will be happening to me. It will be happening for me. And so we dukkher ourselves and bring dukkha into the moment through unawareness. When we have awareness, dukkha ceases.

When we have no awareness, dukkha is arising. It’s two sides of the coin. You can choose how you want to live your life in the present moment. If you want to be aware, mindful and fully aware of what your mental state is, so that you can note it, know it and let it go, then you can live in freedom from this onslaught of craving to be. If you don’t want to do that, if you just want to let it come into every sense experience that you have got, create a sense of self, prepare yourself for the ups and downs of life, the vicissitudes of life. Lots of unpleasantness, lots of pleasantness. You’ll be swirling like in a washing machine. Swirling around. Swirling around by being conditioned 59 by pleasantness and unpleasantness if you are unable to note it, know it and let it go.

Our meditation technique this week is designed to understand the nature of our mind. To see how it is functioning, real data in real-time. And you’re not just listening to me telling you about this, you’re going to practice it. We are going to witness it for ourselves. The Buddha’s teaching is not something you believe in. It is not a belief-system. The Buddha never asked us to believe something. He asked us to investigate for ourselves and to understand for ourselves. That is what the Buddha’s teaching is all about. It’s about understanding. He never says, hey, come and believe me. He says, have a look at that and understand it. He never asked us to believe anything. He asked us just to do the practice and experience it for ourselves. You will all be able to experience some level of dhamma on this retreat. To some level or another, you will all experience some aspect of nature that is arising and passing away in your mental and physical process.

If we don’t observe what is going on, when we see something or when we hear something, then we are very quick to react. We normally react with aversion or attraction, attachment. If it is pleasant, we’ll like it, we want it, more. If it is unpleasant, we dislike it, we push it away, we get rid of it. This is what we do. If we are unmindful, we just go through life, processing things in this way. Unpleasant and push away. Pleasant, more. Unpleasant, push away. Pleasant, more. If we are surrounded by unpleasantness, then we will have to work out a way to try to escape by searching for something pleasurable. Trying to open the fridge door, get some food out, put the music on, find some kind of pleasurable distraction to take us away from the present moment. Up until now, our only way to be dealing with any dukkha-states has been through sensuality. Trying to find something nice to eat, something nice to look at, something nice to listen to, something nice to touch of clothing, touch of another person. We go searching for those things. Drugs, for alcohol, for sex, for food, gambling. We search for things to pull us out from our dukkha.

Dukkha is manifesting in the present moment continuously. And this is the first noble truth. The Buddha said, there is dukkha. He’s doesn’t say, you are dukkha. He doesn’t say, your life is dukkha. He doesn’t say, the world 60 is dukkha. All he says is, there is dukkha. There it is! Right there! Where? Here! This thing. This is where dukkha is arising, and this is where dukkha is ceasing. Only here! Dukkha is not out there. Suffering, the Buddha is talking about, is not outside. He is talking about this thing here. So let’s have a look inside. See if you can see this dukkha arising in the present moment. If we can see the dukkha that is arising in the present moment, we will also see the craving that produces that dukkha and also see where that dukkha ceases to exist. It’s called walking the noble eightfold path and we’ll be doing that this week.

When we see things that we like, when we hear things that are pleasant, we just take those things as being good things. We like them, we love them, we want to get them, we want to hold them, we want to keep them, we want to become the owner of them. That is mine, that is happening to me. If it is not mine, it’s not good enough. Living in a fancy house, wow, it would be great, if we owned that place. Why? What is great about owning it? Anyway you get to live in it already, why do you need to own it? Why will owning be any better? It’s just the story of your self. The story of me. It wants stuff, it clings and tries to hold on to stuff. It tries to accumulate things. It’s constantly seeing what the mind, what craving is doing. It’s just trying to build an identity for itself. It is very effective, it’s very skillful, it does so very efficiently. It’s creating a personality, building an identity for itself and each moment is used as a little backup, a little prop, a little crutch to keep the show rolling. To keep this mirage of a person rolling on. It keeps having to identify to things in the present moment to keep backing it up. To keep backing up the story that this is somebody. That there is somebody here.

Vipassana insight blows this apart. When we see things clearly with insight, we understand that things are impermanent, things are unsatisfactory and things are ultimately out-of-control and non-self. They don’t belong to anybody. It’s not happening to anyone. It’s just happening. How it happens, we will talk about as the days go on. Why it’s happening, we’ll talk about as the days go on.

For our purposes here today, it’s happening. All we have to do is observe it. We have to watch it. We are watching the physical sensations in the body. Really pay attention to the movement inside the body when the breath goes 61 in and out. Don’t pay so much attention to the breath. Pay a lot of attention to the sensations created by the breath. What does it feel like to be inside the body knowing those physical sensations? So just be mindful of whatever is arising in the present moment. That’s what our practice is all about. We are noting, we are knowing and we are letting go moment after moment after moment. And this leads us to a state of concentration, a stabilized mode of perception in which we start to see things as they really are. When we see things as they really are, the mind can no longer build a sense of self from that object in that present moment. If you see something clearly with Vipassana insight, it’s impossible for consciousness to build a story and identify with that object. We have seen it clearly. Clear seeing has taken place. You will stop identifying with that physical sensation. It’s not me, mine or I. You will stop identifying with that thought process, that habitual craving that you may have. You will stop identifying with some aversion state that often arises. You will stop identifying with many different things if you can keep your awareness in the present moment, noting, knowing and letting go. So that is what our practice is all about this week.

We are going to do some walking meditation now. Just to remind you about the walking meditation. We find a place outside, nice and calm, come to attention, standing, become aware of the standing posture, feel the feet as they are touching the floor, touching the sand or wherever you are standing, come inside the body, lower your head, keep your mind inside the body, don’t allow it to go wandering into the jungle, wandering on to somebody’s body. Keep your mind inside and start gently making movements lifting, moving, placing. Lifting, moving, placing. And try to walk from one end to the other end. It can be 12 or 15 steps, lifting, moving, placing, lifting, moving, placing. Try to take each one as a single event. Lifting. Finished. Moving. Finished. Placing. Finished. Lifting. Finished. Moving. Finished. Placing. Finished. Dividing your experience up into discrete individual moments where you can note and see what is happening in that present moment experience. We are going to start to divide the stream of your life up and start just to divide and conquer, if you like, the flow of mental and physical phenomena arising and passing away extremely rapid up until now. Your life has very 62 successfully fooled you, believing that you are somebody. This Vipassana is going to remove this false view so that you can start to live in a lot more freedom and a lot more peace and a lot less dukkha.

6. Day 2, afternoon

We are going to have a look at the mental aspect of our experience. We are going to look at what is known as vedana or feeling. It plays a very important role in the Buddha’s teaching. Vedana or feeling is one of the four satipatthanas. It’s the second satipatthana, the second foundation of mindfulness.

We use the analogy of the Shwedagon pagoda in Yangon, Myanmar. There is 100 meter tall pagoda on top of a huge platform. In order to get to that platform, you need to walk up one of four gigantic staircases. You can use any of the stairways to walk up to the platform, to walk up and see the pagoda.

Here we are using the pagoda as an analogy for our present moment experience and we’re using the four staircases for the four foundations of mindfulness. We can establish awareness in the present moment using one of the four foundations. You can use the body door, that we have been looking at already – the physical sensations and postures of the body. We can also use feeling – pleasantness and unpleasantness. We can use our mind state in that present moment experience as a foundation for mindfulness. And we can also use thoughts or reactions, that come in the present moment experience as a foundation for mindfulness. Depending on your skill, you can use anyone of the four foundations of mindfulness to establish awareness and 100 wisdom in the present moment. You can choose. All four are available. Just like the stairways that lead to the pagoda platform, they are all available for us. We can use the body, feelings, emotions or thoughts to establish our awareness in the present moment.

6.1. Feeling

So feeling is one of the four foundations of mindfulness. Feeling has been isolated because of importance of it’s role in the Buddha’s teaching. Feeling is also one of the five aggregates. Again it’s isolated from the other mental aggregates of perception and sankharas, conditional formations. It’s part of nama, the mind, but it’s separated. Feeling also plays an important role in the paticca samuppada, dependent origination, as feeling is the cause and condition for craving. Craving is the cause and condition for dukkha. So feeling plays a very important role in the teachings of the Buddha. So we need to understand precisely what feeling is.

Feeling or vedana is the cause and condition for delight and lust. It’s based on feeling, particularly pleasant feeling, that we start liking things, we start delighting in things. Lust arises in the mind. Lust for being, craving for being arises.

Feeling is simply the affective tone, or affective component of our experience. It’s the flavor of our experience. Feeling is either pleasant, unpleasant or neutral. There are three types of feeling: pleasant, unpleasant, neutral. Structurally one type of feeling will be arising in the present moment, continuously, with the other of the five aggregates, and passing away. Arises and passes away. It is just the flavor. It’s not the physical sensations in the body – they are the four elements, they are physical – it is not the emotional state, that we find ourselves in sometimes, that is a mind state. Feeling is something different. Feeling is just the unpleasantness of an experience or pleasantness of an experience, just that. Yet it plays an enormous role, because feeling is known as the citta sankhara. Or the mind conditioner. Our minds have been conditioned by feeling. We are going to need to understand feeling, not only on a general level, but on an intuitional level, on a meditational level. We are going to have to see for ourselves how pleasant feeling conditions liking and craving that leads to dukkha, and unpleasant 101 feeling conditions disliking and aversion which also leads to dukkha, if feeling is not noted and known. Then it will be appropriated and identified with, it will be subjectified, it will be for me. As it’s arising in nature, it’s just pleasantness or unpleasantness arising and passing away. It doesn’t belong to anybody. It’s just a feature of the mind and body process. It is just one part, the tone or the flavor of the experience whether it’s pleasant or unpleasant.

We need to really note it quickly, when it starts to arise, before it starts to condition the mind and before we loose our awareness and wisdom in the present moment, before we get taken away by a pleasant story or an unpleasant experience. We need to be able to note this in the present moment clearly. Feelings are impermanent, they arise and pass away, extremely rapidly, they are conditioned, they are dependently arisen. They are the subject to fading away and ceasing.

There are six types of feeling: feeling born of eye contact, of ear contact, of nose contact, of tongue contact, of body contact, and feeling born of mind contact. Contact is that type of state where our internal base and the external objects, that relate to that base, contact each other and consciousness arises. Consciousness arises joined with feeling. They arise and pass away. Mind and matter and consciousness arise and pass away together at the six sense doors. So there is feeling which can be pleasant, unpleasant or neutral at the eye door, that can be pleasant, unpleasant or neutral at the ear door, mind door and so on.

If you feel a pleasant feeling, you won’t feel an unpleasant or neutral feeling at that moment. Feeling is mutually exclusive to the moment. It is either pleasant, unpleasant or neutral. And then it passes away. Of course, you can have all kinds of thoughts or emotional states towards a feeling. Feeling will arise and pass away, rapidly replacing one another.

The Buddha was asked by the wanderer Pataliputta: «Why does feeling arise in the present moment? Why in every single moment is it pleasant, unpleasant, neutral? Why is that part of the structure of our experience, the structure, the nature that we’re subjected to?» – «Having done an intentional action through body, speech and mind whose resultant is pleasant, one feels pleasure. Having done an intentional action through body, speech and mind – that’s karma, having created some karma, some intentional action, some 102 cetana; cetana, intention, is karma – whose resultant is unpleasant, one feels unpleasantness.» So the feelings that we experience in the present moment are the resultants of old intentional structures. Old karma, that we have created. That remains latent. Kama sati, karmic energy, as a potentiality, only has an opportunity to arise when its conditions are in place. If there is some condition in place for it to hatch and manifest, to bloom, then it will! And it will give its fruit. Either pleasant or unpleasant or neutral. If the karma that was created was wholesome or unwholesome than the resultant will be experienced as pleasant or unpleasant feeling, respectively.

When they bubble up, they don’t belong to anybody. It’s not you, you didn’t create an intentional structure. There is nobody here that is creating karma. Karma is creating itself. Reaction. The five aggregates are creating themselves every moment. And when that resultant bubbles up, if we are unmindful, if we fail to activate our awareness and wisdom in the present moment and note and know it, see it clearly and let go of it, so that it is not a base for the arising of self, then that feeling will simply be appropriated and identified with. The feeling will happen to me, it will be mine, the feeling will be subjectified. Then we just react to it with liking if it’s pleasant or with disliking if it’s unpleasant. Of course that reaction is new karma. That’s a new intentional structure through body, speech and mind which will give a resultant to be experienced as pleasant or unpleasant feeling. So it keeps looping. Around and around like this. This is what ignorance is. That is the nature of ignorance. Unawareness in the present moment. If we are unable to see this structure happening in real-time in our mediation practice, we won’t fully understand what it is to be stuck in samsara. This is a very tight and concrete structure. It fits together very well. It has been operating successfully and managing itself for a very long time. This is its latest manifestation sitting here on the meditation mat.

Receiving resultants, reacting towards them, creating new karma, receiving resultants, reacting towards them, creating new karma, receiving resultants, reacting, creating new karma – moment after moment. Each of these moments giving us a little taste of me or mine. When these little moments are added up together they produce a sense of I, a self, a me, an identity. They give this mind and body process, which is flowing on in nature, 103 to believe it is somebody. It’s alive. It’s calling itself something. In fact, our parents called it something. We started to maintain that name as well.

We need to be very careful about pleasantness or unpleasantness. Pleasantness and unpleasantness is the trigger. Whenever you find this triggering you, whenever you find yourself reacting, if you feel you’re about to explode in anger, or you can feel an addiction urge arising, a liking and a disliking, a pushing and pulling away, have a look at the feeling. Start to note the pleasantness or unpleasantness of the situation and you will be able to free your mind from those states. The most important thing is not to appropriate feeling or identify with it. The Buddha tells us, that the way leading to the origination of identity view, to the arising of identity view, we regard the internal base, the external base, the consciousness that arises when these two meet together, and the feeling born from those bases touching together. When we take these things as mine, this I am, this is myself, that’s when identity view arises. Identity view ceases when we stop appropriating and identifying the internal base, the external object, the consciousness that arises in that moment (the knowing), the contact of that base and the feeling of that base. These five things. If we can stop appropriating and identifying with them at the six sense bases, then we are free. We are free of identity view. Identity view is the large leash that keeps us bound to samsara. It’s the view that the mind and body process comes to believe that it is someone. The Buddha’s teaching is to remove that sense of I from the picture. Remove the sense of me from our experience so that we can go back to nature. The Buddha says, that all the conditioned phenomena, all the mental and physical phenomena, that we are identifying with are dukkha. The whole lot. All the physical sensations, all the mental sensations, the thoughts, the emotions, the pleasant, the unpleasant, all of them. It’s all conditioned nonsense arising and passing away. It doesn’t belong to anybody. We need to be able to see this if we want to breakthrough. If you want to evolve as a spiritual being and remove the sense of self, remove the ego, remove the duality, that we have put into the moment, where there is a me and a world. That’s how we are operating. With separation. When we remove the sense of self, there is no separation at all. There is a knowing. And it’s blissful.

We need to understand and see these feelings as impermanent, as suffering 104 and as non-self. Of course pleasantness is going to arise. The Buddha still calls it dukkha. It’s important to understand here, what the Buddha is asking us to let go of, is not the pleasant feeling but the attachment and identification that we developed towards pleasant feeling. Pleasant feelings will arise, it is their nature to arise, old karma is unfolding. You will experience some pleasantness and some unpleasantness in your life. And there is nothing wrong with that. That is nature. What the Buddha’s teaching is all about, is stopping the identification with the feelings. That gives us the problem. When we start identifying with something unpleasant, than it is dukkha right away. When we start identifying with something pleasant, then it is dukkha when that object passes away, when we loose it. Dukkha arises through attachment. Freedom arises through non-attachment.

But don’t think that you have to give up all those special activities that you like to do. You don’t have to give up your life to practice the Buddha’s teaching. Pleasantness, pleasant activities, friends who are nice, these are all ok things. You can still eat, go on holidays, listen to music but don’t get attached to the pleasantness. Stop identifying with it and free yourself from it. Then you will be able to enjoy the world without an ego getting in the way. It’s a much higher, more fulfilling sense of enjoyment. There is a bliss that arises when you can let go of the pleasure that’s created through sensuality. At the moment we don’t see anything higher than the pleasures that arise through the five physical sense doors. They give us so much pleasure! Or we pleasure ourselves through our own thinking, our own rumination.

In the dependent origination, between the six sense bases and feeling is what is known as contact or phassa. Phassa is the point in the sense perception process, where we activate our awareness and note, know and let go right at the point where consciousness is arising. When there is an internal base and an object, consciousness arises. Ear consciousness arises when there is an ear and a sound. Body consciousness arises when there is a body and something touching the body. Sight consciousness arises when you have an eye ball and there is sufficient light and visible forms available. When these two touch together, it is called contact. They cause the arising of consciousness in the present moment. We need to be able to note right at that point of contact. Right at the six sense bases where they’re arising and 105 passing away. It’s right at that point of contact, if it’s unnoted and unknown, that craving enters the sense perception process. Craving for being gets in there. This very strong desire to be something, to become somebody. Unfortunately it’s rife in our society. Our whole education system is pushing us to become something. The subjects we have to choose. The society, our family, friends all are pushing us to become something. This craving for being is defilement. It is the cause of dukkha. The Buddha told us to note it, know it and let it go. Free our mind from it. Craving for being has an opportunity to enter the sense perception process right at the point of contact. It’s conditioned by the feeling that’s arising there.

In the Madupindika sutta, the Buddha gives a very succinct description of the sense perception process. «When there is eye and physical forms, eye consciousness arises, the meeting of the three is contact, with contact as condition feeling. (The grammar then changes in the Pali text.) What one feels, that one perceives. What one perceives that one thinks about. What one thinks about that one mentally proliferates.» Mental proliferation means appropriation and identification. It means taking things as mine, this I am, this is myself. Up to the point of feeling, the sense perception process is objective. There is no subjectivity in there. Eye, plus form, eye consciousness arises, the meeting of the three is contact, with contact as condition, feeling. This is an impersonal process that is happening to nobody. If there is no awareness and wisdom in that moment, when this contact is taking place, then craving sneaks in. What one feels, that one perceives. What one perceives, that one thinks about. It is already starting happening to somebody. The feelings and the perceptions and the thoughts are for somebody, happening to somebody. They are mine. So subjectification has taken place. And then mental proliferation besets a person with respect to past, present and future visible forms cognized through the eye. It happens extremely rapidly. You will need to be continuous in your meditation practice to be able to catch it. You won’t catch it quickly or easily. But if you are diligent, if you are practicing correctly, moment after moment, without any desire to try and get any results – we need to drop that desire, we need to check our attitude – if you are just practicing continuously, «bum», and you will drop into the present moment, and you will see things as they are. The mental and 106 physical phenomena will become quite clear to you. You will be able to see them arising and passing in the moment, you will be able to see mental and physical phenomena, that have been subjectified and are under the control of craving, and you will be able to see mental and physical phenomena, that have escaped the subjectification process, that are free data, that pass away, that are no longer useful or able to continue the illusion that there is somebody here. It is only because we are not looking that we think we are someone. As soon as you start looking, you won’t be able to find anyone there. It is impersonal. It’s just a natural process unfolding, like a tree growing in the forest! It starts small, then grows up, then gives fruit, and then it gets old and falls over. Nothing much different than this body here. It gets born, it grows old, it gets sick and dies. All the time we’re holding on to it preciously thinking it’s me. Actually it’s a huge burden.

It is a real hassle to have a body. You have to take it everywhere, you have to feed it, you have to wash it, clean it and cloth it, make it look fancy sometimes. It is like a 30 kg backpack. You have to take it all over the place with you. It’s got six radars out there collecting information through the sense doors. We spend most of our lives taking care of this body. We think it is really important. It is just earth, water, fire and air. It’s just the four elements arising and passing away. Because it has got a nice conceptual structure around it, we have come to think it is me. We are willing to work for 50 years, to borrow large amounts of money from the bank to buy a concrete room to keep it at night. Why are we doing that? We need a fancy room to keep it, this rotten log of festeringness. If we don’t see it clearly we’ll take it very seriously, we take our life very seriously. We’ll take ourselves very seriously. We get upset when people challenge it. When we start to see it more clearly though, it starts to loose its importance to us.

So the six sense bases of contact are impermanent and are subject to change. A pleasant feeling or an unpleasant feeling that arises from impermanent bases, do you think that such a feeling can possibly be permanent? No! It is also impermanent. It also passes away very, very rapidly.

Notice when the dog barks. It takes half a second. It’s just a quick amount of noise and then it’s gone. Finished, it’s passed away. But our mind takes this fraction of a second of noise and starts to spin. «What’s that dog 107 doing here? Why is there a dog here? Which dog is it? I don’t like dogs. My dog at home…» – and then you get into a fantasy about dog walking. You’re gone for five minutes…bring yourself back to the present and start again. The early days on the meditation retreat are very much like that. We need to activate our awareness continuously. Keep activating, keep pulling yourself back inside. Use the ear door to pull you back in. Sound is always there. We are not listening to sounds. That means we have gone out if we are listening. We are holding our awareness inside the body, just noting that hearing is occurring. If you can do that, you’ll find that you can come back to the present very rapidly. Hold it there for a bit. Bring your mind into the body. Start to pay attention to the rise and fall. Get a few in, and then, wooop, it’s gone again. Activate your awareness, come back to the present, keep doing it. We are just training. We are training the mind as it runs out. We bring it back. Like when we’re fishing. Bring it back. Than it runs out. Bring it back. Finally, it is so tired, that we can just bring it in. It won’t find any interest in going out anymore and we can hold it inside. That’s when our meditation really starts to stabilize, when we can develop awareness of the body. Full awareness of the body is what we want to develop.

The importance of feeling and its place in the Buddha’s teaching is also shown to us by the Bramachalla sutta (first discourse in the large collection Diga Nikaya). Brama means the highest, challa is a net. The Buddha throws a net across 62 views. In the Buddha’s time, he identified 62 different views. There were various philosophers, recluses and meditators and priests and brahmins. All of them had their own ideas how the world was functioning, they all had their philosophical standpoint. They all had their different views on how the sense of self arises and what it is. All the monks and nuns in Burma have to study it for their exams. It is an important sutta.

It goes something like this: «When those ascetics and brahmins, who are speculators about the self in the past, who are speculators about self in the future, who have fixed views about the self, who put forward views about the self in these 62 ways, it is merely the feeling of those who do not know and do not see, the delight, worry and vacillation of those immersed in craving.» These 62 views are all conditioned by contact. Present moment, contact, contact arising at the physical doors. «That all these speculators 108 should experience feeling without contact that is impossible. They experienced the feelings, pleasant, unpleasant and neutral by repeated contact through the six sense basis. With feeling as condition craving arises.» Luckily the Buddha gives us some instruction. «When a monk understands as they really are, the arising and passing away of these six sense bases, when he understands the satisfaction of the six sense bases, when he understands the danger of the six sense bases, and the escape from them, then he knows that which goes beyond all these views of self.»

So when we understand the point of contact, where feeling is arising, we understand the arising and passing away of feeling, when we know it to be an impermanent, dependently arisen, conditioned phenomena. We see it arising, we see it passing. We see the satisfaction that we get from feeling, the pleasantness, the joy, the delight and lust we get from feeling, and also see the danger that feeling presents to us. In fact, that feeling is the cause and condition to delight and lust and craving. If we see the danger of feeling, than we are able to let it go. We move beyond feeling. We see the escape from feeling. So these five things are to be seen and understood. We know the arising of feeling, we make a note when it’s arising, when it’s there. We make a note when it’s passed away. Pleasantness there. Now it’s gone. We know the arising and passing. We know the satisfaction. We know the danger. And then we see the escape from it. When we have completely let go of feeling, in that moment, we’re free. No self arises in that moment. That’s a moment of freedom.

Our job as meditators is to just extend that moment out indefinitely as much as we can. In the beginning stages we only get a fraction of a second as a look but then the curtain opens and stays open for a little bit longer, for seconds or minutes, maybe for hours where we’re experiencing the mind and body process without a sense of self. And it’s gone when we are right there in the present moment. We are free from dukkha.

«That one shall here and now make an end of suffering, without abandoning the underlying tendency to lust or pleasant feeling, without abolishing the underlying tendency to aversion for painful feeling, without removing the underlying tendency to ignorance with regard to neutral feeling, without abandoning ignorance and arousing true knowledge, this is impossible.

109 When one is touched by a pleasant feeling, if one delights in it, welcomes it, remains holding to it, then the underlying tendency to lust lies within one.

When one is touched by a painful feeling, if one sorrows and grieves and laments, weeps, beating ones breast and becoming distraught, then the underlying tendency to aversion still lies within one.

When one is touched by a neutral feeling, if one doesn’t understand as it actually is, the arising, passing, the satisfaction, the danger and the escape in regard to that feeling, then the underlying tendency to ignorance lies within one.»

So you see that coming to understand feeling, noting the pleasantness or unpleasantness of a particular situation is very important if we’re to remove ourselves from these defilements. If we are to let go of lust, aversion and ignorance. Greed, hatred and delusion. When we can remove these from our present moment experience, then we see that which is beyond, when our Vipassana insight becomes strong. Phassa or contact does not yield a self. This is the point where the knowledge of arising and passing away is observed. The Buddha called it the deathless state. He called it the amata dathu. Amata, there is no death occurring in that present moment experience because there is nobody there who dies. It’s the deathless because we moved beyond the realm of birth and death. Birth and death are concepts that relate to a person, that relate to an individual. There needs to be somebody before there can be birth and death. If the mind and body process are not thinking of themselves as somebody, if they have escaped that delusion, if they have uprooted that ignorance in that present moment, if they have developed awareness and wisdom in that present moment, then they can escape feeling and they escape dukkha. And they realize the deathless, the arising and passing away of phenomena.

When we are considering feeling, it is important that we don’t get confused between feelings and sensations in the body or mind states in the mind. To give you a little example, the four foundations of mindfulness, the four walkways to the pagoda platform, are always available for us to use. We can walk to the present moment using anyone of the staircases. For example a mosquito comes and bites you on the arm:

110 In that present moment experience there can be some tingling, or itching, maybe a little bit of heat occurring. That is a physical sensation. That’s the first foundation, mindfulness of the body or kaya-nupassana. We can direct our awareness and wisdom in the present moment on that physical sensation. We have established mindfulness on the body, on a physical sensation.

If we choose to, we can establish our awareness on the unpleasantness of that situation. There is also an experience of unpleasantness. We can establish our awareness just on the unpleasantness. It’s called mindfulness on feeling, vedana-nupassana. Just on the unpleasantness, not the physical sensation on what our mind is complaining and whinging about, just the unpleasantness. You can establish awareness on feeling.

If we want to have another look at this situation, we can look at our mind, the third foundation of mindfulness. The citta-nupassana. We can establish our awareness on the mind state, which is most probably aversion. Aversion is that type of dissatisfied mind. We are bitten by a mosquito, the mind is full of aversion. That’s the third foundation. We can use that to establish our awareness on, to note and know that present moment experience. To blow it apart with our awareness and wisdom so that it is not used as the base for the arising of me, mine or I. We don’t go into it and start to think, «Oh, my itchy arm. Why does it happen to me all the time?»

We can establish our awareness on the fourth foundation of mindfulness, dhamma-nupassana, which is the reaction process, the thought process, the karmically active process. That’s the actively pushing away, that kind of energy of disliking, pushing. It’s also available to us as a foundation for mindfulness.

The physical sensation – the itchiness, or feeling – the pleasantness, or the mind state – the aversion in the mind, or mind objects – our reaction of disliking towards it. So in four ways we can become mindful of a present moment experience. This is a very simple example. It happens moment after moment, after moment. That is what our experience is. The five aggregates arising together and ceasing together, in every moment of our conscious experience, there will be a physical sensation, there will be some feeling, 111 there will be some mind state and there will be some reaction going on.

We are establishing our awareness stepping back from what is going on. We are establishing awareness in the present moment so that we can see things as they really are. When we can see things as they really are, we can begin to let go of them. We do let go of them. If we are unable to do this, then we’re just subjected to sensuality. If we’re unable to note and know in the present moment, if we can’t activate our awareness and be aware of our own mind states, then we have nothing else to do but simply follow along the flow of craving wherever it takes us. We become the slave of craving. The slave of our own mind. And the only way we know to escape from dukkha, is through sensuality looking for something pleasant, something enjoyable, forms cognizable by the eye, or sounds cognizable by the ear, sent cognized through the nose, tastes cognized through the tongue, sensations cognized through the body. That will be our only escape to our dukkha when it’s arising. Seeking out one of these things. The pleasure and joy that arises, dependent on the cords of sensual pleasure is simply called sensual pleasure. The Buddha regarded it as a filthy pleasure, a false pleasure, an ignoble pleasure. «I say this kind of pleasure that it should not be pursued, that it should not be developed, that it should not be cultivated, that it should be feared.» He knew the danger this sensual pleasure leads to. It certainly doesn’t lead to awakening. It leads to burying deep into samsara. We are delighting in the cause of dukkha.

So controlling our reactions to these three feelings, the pleasant, unpleasant and the neutral. Neutral feeling probably takes up 98% of our time. There is maybe 1% pleasantness and 1% unpleasantness. But those little 1% are what we live for. Desiring something delightful and pleasant. Trying to escape from the unpleasantness. If it’s slightly unpleasant we try to change it, try to get rid of it, searching for something pleasant.

When we are in stress or a difficult situation such as an emotional break-down, we go for a snack, chocolate, ice cream, or some other kind of snack, just to try to distract ourselves from the dukkha that we got ourselves in. But the correct strategy is to use awareness and wisdom, to note and know and let go. Don’t go looking for outside options to cure yourself. The best cure we have, is right here, the mind and body process itself, awareness 112 and wisdom.

So controlling our reactions to these three feelings through attention and observation at the very point where defilement arises, is the heart of mind training. That’s what we are doing here. We are training the mind in non-reaction. This does not mean that we become boring or a rock in the forest, sitting there completely unmoved and unchallenged by anything. Of course, you can still have some fun in your life. The Buddha is not advocating the death of all fun, just don’t get attached to it. Or as Ajahn Chah says, «you can enjoy as much salt as you like as long as you don’t find it salty».

So we restrain our senses. We keep an observation on our six sense doors. We are watching, we are noting, knowing and letting go each moment activating our awareness and seeing what’s there. When we have activated our awareness, there is always going to be an object. Either a physical object or a mental object – we can choose. All we have to do is to maintain our awareness and wisdom. Awareness will take us to the object and penetrate it clearly. Wisdom allows us to disengage from it and step out of the identification process. In that case it is let go of. Dukkha ceases. Dukkha ceases when wisdom removes ignorance. When wisdom is unable to uproot ignorance, then the flow of paticca samuppada, dependent orientation, must result in dukkha. Awareness and wisdom do have the power over ignorance. If they didn’t have the power, no-one would be able to get enlightened. Because they do have the power, it is possible that we can break free of this mind and body process. We can allow it to do just what it does and we can enjoy the space and freedom of consciousness, which is not addicted to the mind and body process.

14. Day 6, afternoon

This afternoon we’re going to have a look a the second and the third noble truths, the noble truth of the cause of suffering, and the noble truth of the cessation of suffering.

Yesterday we had a look at suffering. There is dukkha. We had a look at how the Buddha analyzes our mental and physical phenomena. He analyzed it into the six sense bases and the five aggregates.

This afternoon, we’re going to have a look how the second and third noble truths are closely related to each other. In fact, one of them, the cause of dukkha, and the other, the cessation of suffering, are really two sides of one coin. When we look at these noble truths together, we are looking at the dependent origination, or paticca samuppada.

14.1. Second noble truth

The Buddha tells us, that the cause of dukkha needs to be seen in order to be eradicated. What is the second noble truth of the arising of suffering? – It’s just this craving that occurs again and again bound up with delight and lust. Seeking delight here and there. Sensual desire, craving for being and craving for non-being.

The cause of suffering is craving for being. It’s just this craving that occurs again and again that is bound up with delight and lust. There is some 228 delighting. That’s why craving can hit its mark so often. We like it. We enjoy being. It enjoys being. It loves to be somebody. That’s why craving’s job is so easy. It’s delighting in itself. And it’s seeking delight here and there. «Now here, now there, seeking fresh delight» at the six sense doors. Craving is seeking delight. It’s seeking being at the six sense doors.

Where does this craving arise? Where does it get established? – «Wherever in the world there is something enticing and pleasurable, there this craving arises and is established.» Wherever there is an object in which it can seek delight, there craving arises. It’s the six sense based nama-rupa.

The ultimate cause of dukkha is ignorance. Ignorance of the four noble truths. Unawareness of the four noble truths. Not knowing, not understanding dukkha and its cause, the cessation and the path. Through not understanding these four noble truths, beings are bound by the leash of craving to samsara. Bound to dukkha.

If we’re to have the ultimate breakthrough, we’ll need to understand, not only dukkha but the cause of it, its fuel, this craving that arises at the six sense bases attaching and delighting in the objects. Delighting in them means finding some pleasure in the sense of self. It delights in it.

The practical real cause of dukkha for us, is the sense of self. Whenever there’s a self, there’s dukkha. We have a lot of self, there’s a lot of selfishness in us, then we’re going to have a lot of dukkha. When our sense of self reduces, then our dukkha reduces. Reduce it a little bit, dukkha reduces a little bit. Reduce it lot, dukkha reduces a lot. Completely reduced, complete reduction of dukkha. It depends on how much self we have, how selfish we are, how big our ego is. This dependence determines how much dukkha we experience. We want to get around with a huge ego and huge sense of self, appropriating and identifying everything we come across, dividing the world into things that are mine and for me and those that are not, then we experience dukkha in every moment. If we want to have a good life, then we need to be aware of this. We need to notice selfishness. It leads to dukkha. Reducing our sense of self leads to a reduction in dukkha. It’s only because there is a «me», there is suffering. When there is no «me», then there is no dukkha. There is no dukkha that applies to anybody. How can it apply to someone that doesn’t exist? It’s only applying when there is a sense of «me». When 229 the «me» is gone, dukkha is also gone. It vanishes. It’s a subjective state.

According to our satipatthana text, craving arises in sixty ways. It arises at the internal base, where it arises in ten different ways. According to the six different doors. So in 60 ways craving manages to penetrate the mind and body process. A little parasite has 60 ways it can get in in a sense experience moment. 60 ways! Our mindfulness needs to be sharp, to be activated to stop this! It’s a very strong and rigid system that’s been set up. It’s difficult to turn it off. Craving always hits its mark unless we have supreme mindfulness and awareness or we can nail the present moment clearly in our mind, see things as they really are and not be trapped or being caught by the infection when it comes to us. We can note it, know it and let it go.

Craving arises at the internal bases, the eye, ear, nose, tongue, body and mind. We take them as being mine or as being me.

Or the external objects that correspond to those doors, the forms, the sounds, the smells, the tastes, the touch and the various thoughts and ideas that come up. These are the objects of the internal bases. These are taken as being for me, or happening to me or being mine.

There is also the consciousness. Six different types of consciousness that arise. The eye consciousness, the ear consciousness, nose, tongue, body consciousness, the mind consciousness. These also are taken as happening to me, or that is me or they are mine in some way.

The contact that happens between these three that is sometimes appropriated and identified with.

Sometimes the feeling that is borne from this, structurally, in the moment, when there is a contact between an external object and an internal base, consciousness arises in this moment of contact, structurally there is also feeling arising in that moment, either pleasant or unpleasant. We are taking that as happening to me. This is my feeling. We are all over it.

Craving enters the perception process as well, the recognition. We pull up old data from the past to try and recognize what this experience of the moment is. We can identify it, recognize it, perceive it. We build a little picture of what’s going on and we start to think about it.

230 Through thinking at the six doors.

Six different types of volitional intention. Volitional intention is a karma process.

Six types of craving, six types of initial thought.

And six types of sustained, evaluative thoughts.

We are trying to subectify anything. Craving tries to get whatever it can. Wherever there’s a gap, wherever, there’s an unmindful spot, that’s where craving can enter. It’s like a rock climber, trying to seek any kind of refuge it can. Wherever there’s a place, it will grab and get hold of trying to keep its existence going. It doesn’t want to let go of the rock face. It wants to be. Craving wants to be something. This is its primordial energy. It’s a subjective state of being. It’s trying to hit a mark. That energy is flowing trying to manifest as someone, as something. It wants to be something. This time around, it’s manifesting as a human! As a being in the sense sphere world. A being that manifests with six sense spheres. And it has been finding its mark pretty well. For our entire lives, craving has been quite successful in infiltrating the moment and building up an idea. It’s become a solid and enduring idea. Lasting for decades. We’re constantly backing it up, supporting it, performing different activities and collecting various things so that we can add to or enhance the sense of self, the sense of me, our subjective state, our being. We’re adding to it trying to reinforce it! If it gets weakened anyway, we feel mortally wounded. Nobody wants to have a weakened sense of self. We are striving to make it stronger. The biggest, the strongest, the fastest, the richest, the funniest – all those states. We’ve been doing that our whole lives. So in 60 ways, 10 by six doors, craving has an opportunity to arise. These are the objects that we need to be noting and knowing, we need to be guarding them from the infiltration of craving to be. We need to get our awareness and wisdom operating and spinning so quickly, that wisdom takes control of the moments, the point of contact, after point of contact, after point of contact. Awareness and wisdom is there, observing, noting, knowing. When it knows, craving can’t land on to that object. Craving can’t do with it as it likes. That object has now been clearly seen by Vipassana. It’s no longer an object which can be subjectified. It can’t be taken as this is mine, this I am, this is my self. It’s out of the game if you like. It’s been neutralized 231 by awareness and wisdom in the present moment. There is a little gap, a little glitch in the matrix. Our job is to make these often and regular. We need to make these gaps more continuous and more sustained. We need to start to break down this very well constructed mechanism turning the neutral environment into one that has been subjectified – dukkhering it. Craving dukkhas the mind and matter process.

A fully enlightened being doesn’t have any dukkha. They’ve removed dukkha, and yet, they still exist. They still manifest. The mind and body process still continues even though craving has been abandoned, uprooted. So it’s possible to still have a mind and body process, still functioning, all the enlightened ones, and the Buddha after his enlightenment, existed dukkhafree. And yet he was still able to perform functions, eating, sleeping, talking, walking, a lot of teaching, all those things.

Now the cessation of craving doesn’t mean that we disappear. It means that our mind and body process is no longer infected by delusion, by ignorance. Greed, hatred and delusion don’t have much chance of arising because there is no self that generates that. It takes a self to be greedy. «I’m greedy, I want.» It’s a subjectified state. «I’m not happy with. I’m angry. I don’t know. I’m deluded.»

In 60 ways appropriating and identifying, craving mistakenly subjectifies the moment and after this is done for many years or decades, there comes to be a strong of sense of «I am». A strong sense of being manifests within the creature. In the mind and body process it comes to a very strong understanding that «I am». A self is established. It seems concrete, it seems continuous. We never question it. If someone asks us, if we really are someone, it seems obvious to us. «Of course, I’m someone, what are you talking about?» If somebody says, you’re no-one. «No, I am someone, I am». Are you? Where are you? I want to see that self. Where is it arising? – It’s just an idea! It’s a dream that infects our reality. It turns our experience of objective nature, of dhamma, into a subjectified experience. An experience of dukkha. When the Buddha is pointing this out, he declares, «there is dukkha». This is how it’s happening. Luckily for us, he also says, «there is an end of dukkha». There is the experience that is the mind and body process which is not undergoing this process of subjectification. The cessation of dukkha is when craving 232 doesn’t enter this stream of experience. That’s the third noble truth. We’ll talk about it very shortly.

So this thing believes it is someone but it’s just a natural impersonal flow of mental and physical phenomena dependently arisen and conditioned. Traveling along on its own journey, naturally unfolding. It’s only because we don’t see it as it really is, that we come to believe this false story that we’ve been told for years and years. Our parents didn’t know and understand, they played along with the game. They may have even enhanced craving’s ability to get into the stream of our flow.

We are just quietly appropriating each sense experience moment building and constructing an ever more present sense of I. We’re developing being. If we are not noting and knowing, we’re developing being. Being is the cause of dukkha. Once there’s being, there’s birth. When there’s no being, there’s no birth. If there’s no personality being constructed than the word «birth» doesn’t apply. Birth is a concept that relates to a person. If there’s no person manifest in that moment, then that’s the end of birth. The cessation of birth. Birth doesn’t take place. Here we’re talking about the birth of the self, the birth of the ego. It’s the idea that I am someone. This is birth. «I am, I’m here».

So the heart of the teaching is to destroy this idea of me, and mine and I, to destroy this idea of subjectivity and to enter the void of suññata, where the mind and matter process is not infected by craving to be, the mind and matter process is empty of self and things pertaining to self. This is an experience of voidness. That world in which a sense of self doesn’t make itself apparent. Empty.

So that’s the second noble truth, the cause of dukkha. Dukkha is produced by this energy, this craving, this wanting, this strong desire to be something. See if you can notice and recognize this in your own mind. See if you notice when it wants to be something. Check your activities and the motivations for your activities. Why are you performing and doing things? Is it to generate a stronger sense of self? Are you deliberately trying to develop a personality? If so, have a look what happens when you do that. Understand that the development of your personality is the development of your dukkha. You’re actually helping craving. You’re opening the door and preparing a 233 seat. «Please come in, sir. Subjectify this experience. Come in and cause some dukkha here. We are all happy here. Come and disturb us!» You don’t want to invite craving into your life! When you notice it, make a note ‘craving, wanting, desiring, wanting to be’.

It seems just like a simple thing. It seems obvious but all of us have experienced that craving to be when we have to make that decision what we are going to be in our life. What are you going to be when you grow up? We think we’ve worked it out in our 20s when we get some job, secure training or get a degree of some sort. «Oh, that’s what I am.» But it doesn’t really stop. Well into your 40s and 50s, we’re still asking the question, what am I going to be when I grow up? – Yes, it doesn’t stop. What am I going to be? And then we become someone and you are not really satisfied with that identity. You want a new one. Something a little bit more funky. Something a little bit cooler. We want to have our own unique niche in the world. Our own unique business card. A CV that is wild and interesting. We can show others. See, how interesting I am! – It’s all to create a sense of self. We think we need to have a strong sense of self to be happy. It’s exactly the opposite. The more we think and spin about ourselves, the more dukkha we get.

We can even cause mental illnesses through obsessive thinking about ourselves. Obsessive thinking about the past and ourself – depression states. Obsessive thinking and planning and worrying about the future and ourself – anxiety states! These states of mind occur because of craving! Because we don’t see the trouble that it’s making. Our society and community is telling us, you have to become something. You have to be someone. And when we don’t know what we want to be, it’s awful. We need to work it out. What am I going to be? Everyone is asking you. What are you going to be? You feel obliged. What is it that we want to be, that we are searching for? Try to see that this energy is craving, is wanting. It really is the cause of dukkha in your life. This is the one, that’s causing the problems. When we can drop it and let it go, when we don’t have to fulfill its desires, running around trying to fulfill craving’s appointments, craving’s wishes – when we’re not doing that, then we’re free. We are free in that moment. We are not a slave of craving. We’re giving up the job of building our personality and our identity. We’re throwing that out of the window.

234 When we note that we start doing that, or when we note, what our motivation for doing a particular action or saying a particular thing is, when we notice that this activity is actually just a self-producing one, then we give it up. We let it go. We change our view, or we change our ability to perform that function. We change our attitude to performing that function. – We can still be helpful, we can still do different things, but we just don’t do it with such a sense of self that it causes identity view to arise.

14.2. Third noble truth

The third noble truth, the cessation of dukkha or dukkha nirodha, is the other side of the coin. It’s the end of suffering. That’s what cessation means. The finish of it, the end of suffering. Where suffering ceases to exist, where it no longer appears.

The Buddha said repeatedly: «Now as before monks, I teach suffer- ing and the cessation of suffering». That’s what the Buddha’s project is. He talks a lot about dukkha and the cessation of dukkha. And this is important to keep in mind, when we investigate the dhamma, when we investigate the Buddha’s teaching for ourselves. When we’re looking to see what the actual teaching is. He was just focussed on these things, dukkha and the end of dukkha. That’s all.

In fact, there was a time, when he was sitting in the forest with a large group of monks and he picked up a hand full of leaves and said, «monks, what is more, the leaves in my hand or the leaves in this great forest?» «Oh, venerable, sir, the leaves in this great forest are many. The leaves in your hand are so few.» «So it is, monks, so it is. The knowledge I have gained is vast, like the leaves in this forest, but the knowledge I’m giving you is just this.» Dukkha and the end of dukkha. Of all the things the Buddha came to understand and came to know, he taught us this: dukkha, the cause of dukkha, the end of dukkha and the path leading to the cessation of dukkha. Only this was worthy in his talks.

These days people want to know what it is that Buddhism teaches. What it teaches in relation to a whole lot of modern day dilemmas. What does Buddhism say about environmental warming, climate change, vegetarianism, poverty, global corporate profit taking, same sex marriage, about 235 a whole range of different things. The truth is, the Buddha didn’t really address any of these subjects. It wasn’t really his thing. We can take some ideas or interference from his teaching and apply it to the modern problems but his project was singular. He was only interested in this problem of dukkha and he was very keen for us to see it. He had the unique ability to teach this dukkha in many different ways to many different people. He had the ability to look at somebody and know how their craving was arising, where they were stuck. He pointed out to them directly. There are many instances of beings becoming enlightened, quite rapidly, after an intervention from the Buddha. He was pointing out where they had gone wrong, what they’re not seeing, how they were clouded by the matrix. And so while he doesn’t deviate from his central concern, he did approach the subject from many different angles according to who he was talking about. All these angles have been recorded in the old Pali texts. We can investigate them for ourselves and see how the Buddha approaches this problem of dukkha and the cessation of dukkha. The myriads of ways, the dozens of ways that he teaches and tells us to look. If we understand what he is talking about and try to follow what he teaches, we will experience for ourselves the nature of the dhamma. People have been doing so, for a thousand years. We will also have that opportunity. The Buddha’s teaching has one taste. He says, «just as the ocean has one taste, the taste of salt, so too this dhamma has one taste, the taste of release.» He wants us to understand dhamma, because he wants us to be free from the dukkherizing process. He wants us to be free from dukkha. So what is this third noble truth? «It is just the reminderless fading away and ceasing, the giving up, the relinquishing, the letting go and reject- ing of that same craving.» It’s the giving up of that craving. Whenever you notice it arising, make a note and give it up. Start to do the work of cessation. Whenever you notice it, relinquish it. Let it go. Start to walk the path. Whenever you note it, there is craving for being starting to play its games and becomes strong in your life, you can quickly remove the suffering that it causes by just noting and knowing it, stepping back. Don’t be fooled by craving any longer. Fading away, ceasing, giving up, relinquishing, letting go and rejecting of that craving to be.

14.3. Nirvana

236 The cessation of dukkha is something that the Buddha called nirvana. He had a very special name to use for this experience where the mind and body process are freed from the craving to be. When we free it through awareness and wisdom, than that experience is called nirvana. Nirvana is not a wonderful palace up in the clouds somewhere. Nirvana is the mind and body process in the present moment unaffected by craving to be. This is how cessation takes place. That’s an experience of nirvana in the here and now. This nirvana the Buddha talks about in the texts, he called it the unborn. It’s the base, the unborn, the unbecome, the unmade, the unconditioned, the transcendent, supra-mundane, ageless, deathless, sorrowless, supreme security from bondage. ‘Bondage’ is the state of being. ‘Supreme security from’ is letting go that craving. We’ll become secure. We reach the base, nirvana, the unconditioned element. It’s not impermanent, it’s permanent. It’s not dukkha, it’s the end of dukkha. It’s still impersonal, it’s not a self. It’s still a state of impersonality, it’s still a state of non-self. You don’t become all of a sudden nirvana. That’s not your true self. It just is what it is. The cessation of dukkha.

Nirvana is also described as the stilling of all formations. The quieting of conditioned phenomena. The relinquishing of all acquisitions. All those things we come to acquire and get – not only the physical things but also our own attributes that we believe we are – it’s the relinquishing of those acquisitions. All the time and all the effort we’ve gone into creating that special identity that we have today, it’s letting all that go and not caring what other people think about us letting it go. We’re evolving in a spiritual way. We are moving beyond our normal mundane lives of eating, sleeping, seeking sensual pleasures, from one sensuality to another, searching for stuff to identify with, to have fun to. As the Buddha says, «delighting». We’re seeking delight. Craving is seeking delight. That’s its speciality. As soon as there is something pleasurable, craving rubs its hand and glee, «uhmm, good, I’ll get easily in here». There is some delighting, creating a sense of being, right here, right now. It loves to be. It loves to develop a self. It likes to work hard on it. It loves dukkha. It’s the cause of dukkha.

Nirvana is described as the destruction of craving and dispassion. So 237 there are many passages throughout the Pali texts describing this state of the bliss of the release when the mind is released from craving. Some of the most beautiful are in the old poetry books. The texts of the terigata and teragata verses, of the elder monks and nuns, where they exclaim in beautiful poetry the bliss of release. Hundreds of monks and nuns explaining, or exalting their experience of nirvana. All of them using slightly different words to explain this experience they uncovered as member of the sangha, the noble sangha, the aria-sangha. Beings who have come across the Buddha’s teaching, had enough intelligence to recognize its importance, put aside a period of their live to intensify their practice and break through, break through to the further shore. And then they tell others about it. Beautiful. Very beautiful. I recommend it if you have a chance to read those texts and translations. Nirvana is sometimes referred to in the texts as the unfashioned. It hasn’t undergone fashioning yet. Sculpting. Creating. It’s called the end. The effluentness. The truth, the beyond, the subtle. The very hard to see. The permanent. The undecaying. The surfacelessness. The non-objectification. Peace. The exquisite. The solace. The exhaustion of craving. The wonderful. The marvelous. The secure. The unafflicted. The passionlessness. The pure. The release. Non-attachment. All these terms signify this state which is beyond craving, where craving can’t enter. The end of craving. The shelter. The harbor. The refuge.

The term «nirvana» was actually a word that the Buddha took from the local language. It didn’t have the meaning of the complete cessation of dukkha. It had a more simple meaning. It was traditionally used in northern India in the fifth century b.c. to describe the going out of a fire. You see the candle burning. When the flame gets put out, we say the flame has «nirvanaed». It’s been put out. The flame burns dependent upon conditions. When its conditions are in place, a flame burns. When there is wax, and wick and heat, when these three are there, the flame burns. When we remove the conditions, one of them at least, heat or wick or wax, then the flame disappears. It’s gone out. It’s no need for us to ask, «oh, where has the flame gone?» This is not what we’re doing. There’s no point in asking «where has it gone?». When we blow out the candle, it doesn’t have to go anywhere. It just ceases to be, because the conditions that were putting it in place have altered, changed. 238 The conditions are impermanent. The conditions on which it stands have changed and so the flame changes. And so it is with this sense of self. It keeps being generated when the conditions are in place and when the conditions are no longer there – nirvana. Cessation.

There are two different types of nirvana. There is nirvana here and now which is experienced when mind and matter are still functioning, but the sense of self ceases. That’s the experience of an enlightened person who still has a mind and body process that they’re carrying around with them. There are people in this country who are enlightened. Monks and nuns and laypeople, who have done the training, experienced it, the mind and body still functioning, still talk. You can have a chat with them. There is nobody there. No-one home! The mind and body process still activated but they don’t have a sense of self. Very interesting to meet these people. If you ever hear about them, please go and visit them.

Then there is the type of nirvana of the enlightened being who passes away. That’s the full nirvana when the mind and body process no longer breathes or is conscious. The normal word we use, «it dies». The person is dead. Death. When an enlightened being dies – it’s a bit of a problem with that sentence – because ‘death’ is a word that applies to a person and if you are fully enlightened you are no longer a person. So this concept death doesn’t apply anymore. Death doesn’t take place for an enlightened one. The elements break apart, and that’s it! Finished. «Done is what had to be done.» Full final release. Consciousness unencumbered. Unhindered by mind and body process. Not attached or identifying with any of it. Free. Released!

The Buddha also used the term suññata, emptiness or voidness to describe his most profound and deepest teachings. It means that all things, all conditioned and unconditioned things are void of self. Suññata. Sometimes we find in the texts, the monks asking the Buddha, «what state does the blessed one normally dwell in these days?» He says, «at the moment I am hanging out in suññata.» Voidness, entering the void where there is no self or things pertaining to self.

So when we put these two noble truths together, the second and the third, they form two sides of one coin, if you like. Two sides of our experience. We can either be noting and knowing and letting go and experiencing 239 the third noble truth, or, we can be appropriating and identifying allowing craving in and we experience the cause of dukkha and dukkha. Two experiences. It’s up to us in the present moment to decide which one we’re going to experience. It’s your choice. Dukkha or nirvana. One of them is very easy. Just lay back and think about yourself all the time. Hmm, just have a nice life of dukkha. Lots of problems. The other one is a little more tricky to practice but a lot more worthwhile – the cessation of dukkha. We’ll have to do something. We have been working very well this week striving to train our mind to be in the present moment so that we can set ourselves up to experience this phenomena. We need to put all the conditions in place and there’s quite a few of them. We’ve been explaining them to you this week. Putting these conditions in place and then to allow the dhamma to unfold.

14.4. Dependent origination

When we join the second noble truth and the third noble truth together, it’s referred to as the paticca samuppada, or dependent arising or dependent origination. It’s the deepest and most profound teaching that the Buddha offers us. In fact, the venerable Ananda, the Buddha’s close attendant for 25 years, once said to the Buddha, «ah, this dependent origination seems so clear and easy to understand. I just don’t get it, why beings don’t under- stand.» The Buddha admonished him: «Oh, do not say so Ananda, do not say so. This teaching is deep and profound as the ocean is wide. It’s through not understanding the dependent origination that beings are bound to sam- sara.» And this is the central teaching we need to understand. It’s the key for unlocking our experience of dhamma.

It teaches us, how the me, or the I arises in the present moment or how the me or the I ceases in the present moment. It’s a very succinct, a very short but also very illuminating teaching. It has 12 forms, 12 different bases on which the sense of self arises. And these 12 bases or these 12 conditioned things are linked together by conditioning processes. They are linked together by what we call the idappaccayatā, or specific conditionality. Each link conditioning the next. «When this is, that comes to be. With the arising of this, that arises. When this ceases, that ceases. With the cessation of this, that ceases.» The things are conditioned. When the conditions are in place 240 they arise. When the conditions are no longer in place, they cease to exist. This is the great teaching that the Buddha uncovered. Conditionality. He saw how the self is a conditioned phenomena. Arising, when there is ignorance and delusion, and ceasing, when there is full awareness and wisdom. He explains this in a little road map. You can often see visual representations of the paticca samuppada. Sometimes it’s in a chain of twelve links. I hope you had a chance to read the notice board down there. Dependent origination is explained there, both in the forward process and in the reverse process, in the dukkha creating process and in the dukkha ceasing process. It’s one coin, with dukkha on the one side and nirvana on the other. It’s either or. When you flip it, it doesn’t land on its edge. We’re either dukkhering ourselves or we’re reaching cessation in the present moment.

14.5. Dukkha creating process

It starts with ignorance. With ignorance as condition volitional formations come to be. The first four items of the dependent origination, ignorance, conditional formations, consciousness and nama-rupa. In the forward direction, if there is ignorance the sankharas or the conditional formations, the intentional structures condition consciousness and nama-rupa. They set that ignorance is conditioning the consciousness in the present moment if we’re unaware. If we’re unaware, the consciousness that arises at the six sense bases has already been infected by ignorance. Just the fact that we’re unaware of that moment, means that we are ignorant in that moment. When ignorance is present, then – consciousness and nama-rupa, which are stuck in a vortex conditioning each other arising at the six sense bases – this consciousness and nama-rupa vortex becomes conditioned by ignorance, and then, when it squeezes out through the six sense bases somewhere, the moment of contact is infected. Contact is there. We can note that contact and see it happening in real time. We can see the infection taking place if there’s ignorance. This happens in a snapshot, this is not a temporal movement. Visual representations of the dependent origination appear to show it traveling through time from one link to the next link and from the next link to another one. But it’s more useful to look at these 12 links stacked upon each other, based upon each other. When we start stacking, they start growing.

241 If we’ve been unable to note in the present moment and unawareness is in that moment, ignorance is in that moment, then the consciousness and nama-rupa which arise at the six sense bases become infected. The feeling that arises joined in this moment becomes a feeling of somebody. A sense of «I» enters in, a sense of «me» enters in into the scene. «It’s my feeling.» That feeling starts to condition the mind. It conditions craving.

When craving comes to be, clinging comes to be. With clinging as condition, being. With being as condition, birth. The next four links show the gradual concentration of the sense of me and mine. The «me» becoming more and more solid. The craving is just taking things as «me» and «mine», happening to me and for me. It does that so rapidly that it builds up a more concrete sense of subjectivity. Clinging, upadana, we come to attavada or the view of self arises. The conceit «I am» starts to arise. It starts to take life, it believes it’s alive. The subjectivity is arising. A person is manifesting in the present moment. Clinging then leads to being, the full sense of self and then a whole history gets mapped out. Birth, that’s the past. Death, that’s the future. These concepts relate to the person that has just been established in that moment.

With ignorance as condition, volitional formations. With volitional formations as condition, consciousness. With consciousness as condition, mind and matter. With mind and matter as condition, the six sense bases. And the six sense bases are infected, the contact is infected, feeling is infected, and then craving, clinging and being come to be. Finally it results in birth, the establishment of an identity and a personality and then sorrow, lamentation, pain, grief and despair. All those states of suffering come into being – just because we’ve been unable to note and know in the present moment. That moment gets infected and becomes a self-moment adding to the pile of self that’s being created along the way, adding to the illusion, reinforcing the illusion.

14.6. Dukkha ceasing process

On the other side, if we can be aware of the present moment, what our Vipassana meditation is all about, if we can note and know rapidly and continuously, if we can increase our noting speed and the number of objects we 242 can note, we’ll start to build up a continuous field of awareness and wisdom. So any time a door opens, we’re knowing what’s there. We’re seeing it clearly. Ignorance is ceasing in that moment. Unawareness is being removed and awareness is replacing it. There is awareness of the moment. When this happens, ignorance is gone. It doesn’t condition the volitional formations. When those volitional formations are no longer functioning, either as greed, hatred or delusion or, on the more positive side, as non-greed, non-hatred, non-delusion, when this conditioning process is not taking place, consciousness doesn’t get conditioned by ignorance. The ‘consciousness and mind and matter’-vortex that arises at the six sense doors, has not been infected by ignorance. That moment is clear, unsubjectified, purified if you like. It’s an experience of dhamma. The contact point seen very clearly – no self there! It’s a moment of freedom. We’ve noted the point of contact at the six sense doors. The feeling that arises, the pleasantness or unpleasantness, is just feeling. It doesn’t belong to anyone. It’s not taken as being good or bad. It ceased to have the opportunity to condition the mind. The pleasantness or unpleasantness is still there, but it has lost its conditioning ability because it’s seen clearly for what it is. It’s not going to be appropriated and identified with. That moment is a moment of knowing, it’s a moment of clear seeing. It’s a Vipassana moment. Feeling doesn’t get taken, craving doesn’t arise. Craving ceases, clinging ceasing, being ceases and so does birth, old age, sickness and death. The whole string of dukkha ceases. Sorrow, lamentation, pain, grief, despair, depression, anxiety, worry, tension – all these things cease in that moment. All these things are concepts that relate to a person and since there is nobody in that moment, those concepts cease to have any validity. They don’t exist.

All we have to do, is to extend this from moment to moment. You can catch it for a second, can we do it for two seconds, three seconds, hold it back, keep noting and knowing, keep noting and knowing, make it continuous. Don’t allow any gaps to occur. See how long ignorance can cease for in the moment. See if you can have that experience of the mind and matter process which is independent of ignorance. Which is not being conditioned by ignorance, which is, in fact, conditioned by wisdom, by true knowledge. When we experience this in the present moment, this is the third noble 243 truth. Cessation. The mind and body process ceases. And the whole edifice collapses in that moment. Our job as meditators is to make sure that we can bring as many of these moments as we can into our experience. The more we can do it, the more we start to alter our understanding of the mind and body process. You’ll start to see it more and more clearly. The things that used to worry us and excite us before, completely loose our attention. Just like when we used to play with dolls or little trucks in the sand pit, when we were very small children, we’ve stopped doing that now because it doesn’t have any interest for us anymore. No longer interesting to play those games. And so it is with developing a sense of self or developing an identity view. It no longer has any interest for us. We just see it as a useless activity while others get a lot of delight from it. We’re just not interested in that anymore. We see the pointlessness of it, we see the futility of it.

We can break this casual process at the point of contact, if our awareness and wisdom is clear. When consciousness and the mental factors arise at the six sense bases, this is where we have to note. If we can be noting at the point of contact continuously, repeatedly, unremittingly, then we can have some possibility of reaching the cessation stage. This is our job. This is what our meditation practice is all about. In fact, this is the role of human evolution. This is what has to be done. Eventually, all beings will escape samsara through this process of letting go of the sense of self, freeing themselves. All of us will have to go through it at some point. Maybe this week, this year or this lifetime or some other time. But this is our destiny, this is our evolution as a species. This is how we move beyond the material realm and enter into the spiritual realm of the enlightened ones. The realm of the beings who are free from dukkha.

For now, it’s important for us to recognize that we may break this causal process and the practicing of satipatthana is the way out of the process that the Buddha so eloquently described. You just need to examine it closely, not the books, we need to examine our own mind. We need to see if the map is reproduced in our own mind and body process. When we see things as they really are in the present moment, it blocks defilement from arising. It’s like we’ve neutralized the field of objects. None of them can be used as a sense of self, as a base for the sense of self. Liking and disliking disappear, judging 244 and comparing – all gone! The knowledge of arising and passing away, it’s not the permanent removal of defilement but it is a little bit of a taste of the deathless state. When we can sit observing the mind, the body and mind process arising and passing at the six sense doors, uninterruptedly, without us subjectifying the process, then we have a taste of the deathless state. A taste of nature. It’s not full nirvana but it’s something getting close to it.

I like to read you now part of the Kaccayanagotta sutta: Kaccayanagotta, just the name of another monk, once visited the Buddha. This text has a special place in the teaching of the Buddha being used by one of the major traditions, the Majjhimas. It’s the central text in their teaching of emptiness and non-self.

Dwelling at Savatthi… Then Ven. Kaccayana Gotta approached the Blessed One and, on arrival, having bowed down, sat to one side. As he was sitting there he said to the Blessed One: «Lord, ‘Right view, right view,’ it is said. To what extent is there right view?»

«By and large, Kaccayana, this world it depends upon a duality, upon the notion of being and upon the notion of non-being. But when one sees the origin of the world as it actually is with correct wisdom – (the second noble truth, the arising of dukkha) – there is no notion of non-being/non-existence in regard to the world. When one sees the cessation of the world as it actually is with correct wisdom, there is no notion of being/existence in regard to this world.

By and large, Kaccayana, this world is shackled by attachments, clingings and adherence. But this one [with right view] does not get involved with or cling to these attachments, clingings, and adherence; he does not take a stand about ‘my self.’ He has no uncertainty or doubt that what arises is only suffering arising; what ceases is only suffering ceasing. His knowledge about this is independent of others. It’s to this way, Kaccayana, that there is right view.

‘Everything exists’: That is one extreme. ‘Everything doesn’t exist’: That is a second extreme. Avoiding these two extremes, the Tathagata teaches the dhamma via the middle: With ignorance as condition, volitional formations. With volitional formations as condition, consciousness. With consciousness as condition, nama-rupa. With nama-rupa as condition, the six sense bases. 245 With the six sense bases as condition, contact. With contact as condition, feeling. With feeling as condition, craving. With craving as condition, clinging. With clinging as condition, being. With being as condition, birth. With birth as condition, aging, death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, distress, despair come to be. Such is the origination of this entire mass of suffering.

But with the remainderless fading away and cessation of ignorance comes cessation of volitional formations. With the cessation of volitional formations, cessation of consciousness. With the cessation of consciousness, cessation of nama-rupa. With the cessation of nama-rupa, cessation of the six sense bases. With the cessation of the six sense bases, cessation of contact. With the cessation of contact, cessation of feeling. With the cessation of feeling, cessation of craving. With the cessation of craving, cessation of clinging. With the cessation of clinging, cessation of being. With the cessation of being, cessation of birth. With the cessation of birth, cessation of aging, death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, distress and despair. Such is the cessation of this entire mass of suffering.»

So this formula, this dependent origination is a map that shows us very clearly our options in the present moment. We are either dealing with ignorance, craving, self and dukkha, or we are dealing with wisdom, the cessation of craving, nirvana and freedom. The choice is ours to make.

18. Chanting

18.1. Morning Chanting

287 Araham sammā-sambuddho bhagavā.
The Blessed One is Worthy & Rightly Self-awakened.

Buddham bhagavantam abhivādemi.
I bow down before the Awakened, Blessed One.

(BOW DOWN)

Svākkhāto bhagavatā dhammo.
The Dhamma is well-expounded by the Blessed One.

Dhammam namassāmi.
I pay homage to the Dhamma.

(BOW DOWN)

Supatipanno bhagavato sāvaka-sangho.
The Sangha of the Blessed One’s disciples has practiced well.

Sangham namāmi.
I pay respect to the Sangha.

(BOW DOWN)

18.1.1. Homage

288

LEADER: Handa mayam buddhassa bhagavato pubba-bhāga-namakāram karoma se:
Now let us chant the preliminary passage in homage to the Awakened One, the Blessed One:

Namo tassa bhagavato arahato sammāsambuddhassa.
Namo tassa bhagavato arahato sammāsambuddhassa.
Namo tassa bhagavato arahato sammāsambuddhassa.

Homage to the Blessed One, the Worthy One, the Rightly Self-Awakened One.

18.1.2. Going for Refuge

289 LEADER: Handa mayam tisarana-gamana-pātham bhanāma se:
Now let us chant the passage going for refuge to the Triple Gem:

Buddham saranam gacchāmi.
I go to the Buddha for refuge.

Dhammam saranam gacchāmi.
I go to the Dhamma for refuge.

Sangham saranam gacchāmi.
I go to the Sangha for refuge.

Dutiyampi buddham saranam gacchāmi.
A second time, I go to the Buddha for refuge.

Dutiyampi dhammam saranam gacchāmi.
A second time, I go to the Dhamma for refuge.

Dutiyampi sangham saranam gacchāmi.
A second time, I go to the Sangha for refuge.

Tatiyampi buddham saranam gacchāmi.
A third time, I go to the Buddha for refuge.

Tatiyampi dhammam saranam gacchāmi.
A third time, I go to the Dhamma for refuge.

Tatiyampi sangham saranam gacchāmi.
A third time, I go to the Sangha for refuge.

18.1.3. Taking the Eight Precepts

290 Pānātipātā veramanī sikkhā-padam samādiyāmi.
I undertake the training rule to refrain from taking life.

Adinnādānā veramanī sikkhā-padam samādiyāmi.
I undertake the training rule to refrain from stealing.

Abrahma-cariyā veramanī sikkhā-padam samādiyāmi.
I undertake the training rule to refrain from sexual intercourse.

Musāvādā veramanī sikkhā-padam samādiyāmi.
I undertake the training rule to refrain from telling lies.

Surā-meraya-majja-pamādatthānā veramanī sikkhā-padam samādiyāmi.
I undertake the training rule to refrain from intoxicating liquors & drugs that lead to heedlessness.

Vikāla-bhojanā veramanī sikkhā-padam samādiyāmi.
I undertake the training rule to refrain from eating after noon & before dawn.

Nacca-gīta-vādita-visūka-dassanā mālā-gandha-vilepanadhārana-manḍana-vibhūsanatthānā veramanī sikkhā-padam samādiyāmi.
I undertake the training rule to refrain from dancing, singing, music, watching shows, wearing garlands, beautifying myself with perfumes & cosmetics.

Uccāsayana-mahāsayanā veramanī sikkhā-padam samādiyāmi.
I undertake the training rule to refrain from high & luxurious seats & beds.

Imāni attha sikkhā-padāni samādiyāmi. [×3]
I undertake these eight precepts.

(BOW THREE TIMES)

18.2. Evening chanting

18.2.1. Recollection of the Buddha

LEADER: Handa mayam Buddhānussati-nayam karoma se:
Now let us recite the guide to the recollection of the Buddha:

Itipi so bhagavā araham sammā-sambuddho,
He is a Blessed One, a Worthy One, a Rightly Self-awakened One,

Vijjā-carana-sampanno sugato lokavidū,
consummate in knowledge & conduct, one who has gone the good way, knower of the worlds,

Anuttaro purisa-damma-sārathi satthā deva manussānam buddho bhagavāti.
unexcelled trainer of those who can be taught, teacher of human & divine beings; awakened; blessed.

18.2.2. Recollection of the Dhamma

LEADER: Handa mayam Dhammānussati-nayam karoma se: Now let us recite the guide to the recollection of the Dhamma:

Svākkhāto bhagavatā dhammo,
The Dhamma is well-expounded by the Blessed One,

Sanditthiko akāliko ehipassiko,
to be seen here & now, timeless, inviting all to come & see,

Opanayiko paccattam veditabbo viññūhīti.
pertinent, to be seen by the observant for themselves.

18.2.3. Recollection of the Sangha

292 LEADER: Handa mayam Sanghānussati-nayam karoma se:
Now let us recite the guide to the recollection of the Sangha:

Su-patipanno bhagavato sāvaka-sangho,
The Sangha of the Blessed One’s disciples who have practiced well,

Uju-patipanno bhagavato sāvaka-sangho,
the Sangha of the Blessed One’s disciples who have practiced straightforwardly,

Ñāya-patipanno bhagavato sāvaka-sangho,
the Sangha of the Blessed One’s disciples who have practiced methodically,

Sāmīci-patipanno bhagavato sāvaka-sangho,
the Sangha of the Blessed One’s disciples who have practiced masterfully,

Yadidam cattāri purisa-yugāni attha purisa-puggalā:
i.e., the four pairs—the eight types—of Noble Ones:

Esa bhagavato sāvaka-sangho—
That is the Sangha of the Blessed One’s disciples—

Ahuneyyo pāhuneyyo dakkhineyyo añjali-karanīyo,
worthy of gifts, worthy of hospitality, worthy of offerings, worthy of respect,

Anuttaram puññakkhettam lokassāti.
the incomparable field of merit for the world.

18.2.4. The Sublime Attitudes

18.2.4.1. Metta – Loving-Kindness

293 Sabbe sattā sukhitā hontu.
May all living beings be happy.

Sabbe sattā averā hontu.
May all living beings be free from animosity.

Sabbe sattā abyāpajjhā hontu.
May all living beings be free from oppression.

Sabbe sattā anīghā hontu.
May all living beings be free from trouble.

Sabbe sattā sukhī attānam pariharantu.
May all living beings look after themselves with ease.

18.2.4.2. Karuna – Compassion

Sabbe sattā sabba-dukkhā pamuccantu.
May all living beings be freed from all stress & pain.

18.2.4.3. Mudita – Sympathetic Joy

Sabbe sattā laddha-sampattito mā vigacchantu.
May all living beings not be deprived of the good fortune they have attained.

18.2.4.4. Upekkha – Equanimity

Sabbe sattā kamma-ssakā kamma-dāyādā kamma-yonī kamma-bandhū kamma-patisaranā.
All living beings are the owners of their actions, heir to their actions, born of their actions, related through their actions, and live dependent on their actions.

Yam kammam karissanti kalyānam vā pāpakam vā tassa dāyādā bhavissanti.
Whatever they do, for good or for evil, to that will they fall heir.